<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The father of the faithfull tempted as was more concisely shewed August 31, 1674, at a solemne funeral in the church at Wotton under Edge in the countie of Gloucester / by Giles Oldisworth ...</title>
            <author>Oldisworth, Giles, 1619-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53304</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15932</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12951730</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12951730</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95939</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53304)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 363:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The father of the faithfull tempted as was more concisely shewed August 31, 1674, at a solemne funeral in the church at Wotton under Edge in the countie of Gloucester / by Giles Oldisworth ...</title>
                  <author>Oldisworth, Giles, 1619-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: filmed copy dark and difficult to read.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews XI, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FATHER OF THE FAITHFULL TEMPTED</p>
            <p>As was more <hi>conciſely</hi> ſhewed <hi>Auguſt</hi> 31. 1674, At a SOLEMNE FUNERAL in the <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH,</hi> AT <hi>WOTTON under EDGE in the</hi> Countie <hi>of</hi> Glouceſter.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. Aug.</hi>
               </bibl> Tota vita humana est tentatio.</q>
            <p>By <hi>GILES OLDISWORTH.</hi> A. M. and <hi>Rector</hi> of <hi>Burton</hi> on the <hi>Hill</hi> in the ſame <hi>Countie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OXFORD. Printed by HENRY HALL. 1676.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:95939:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>HEN: CLERKE Vice Cancel.</hi> OXON.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Jan. <hi>30. 1676.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95939:2"/>
            <head>To the Lady <hi>Crofts,</hi> the vertuous <hi>Conſort</hi> of my very good Lord, <hi>Herbert,</hi> by <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> Lord <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Hereford.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="genealogy">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Regni </seg>1 Edw. 16.</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Domini </seg>1288</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>R <hi>Lancelot Oldiſworth</hi> of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifax</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> Kt. took to wife <hi>Bridget,</hi> daughter of <hi>VVilliam Ramſey</hi> of the ſame <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</hi> Their ſon was <hi>Maurice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Regni </seg>2 Edw. 13.</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Domini </seg>1320</label>
                  <hi>Maurice Oldiſworth,</hi> Husband of <hi>VVinifred</hi> daughter to <hi>Steven,</hi> the brother of <hi>VValter Stapleton,</hi> L. Bp. of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> had iſſue <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Regni </seg>3 Edw. 18.</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Domini </seg>1344</label>
                  <hi>Lancelot Oldiſworth</hi> married <hi>Alice,</hi> daughter of <hi>Thomas Frie</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95939:3"/>of <hi>Devon-ſhire, Gent.</hi> he begat <hi>Maurice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Regni </seg>2 Rich: 1.</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Domini </seg>1377</label>
                  <hi>Maurice Oldiſworth</hi> took to wife <hi>Gennet,</hi> daughter of <hi>Iohn Philpot</hi> L. Mayor of <hi>London.</hi> His ſon was <hi>Lancelot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Regni </seg>4 Hen. 3.</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Domini </seg>1402</label>
                  <hi>Lancelot Oldiſworth</hi> was Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to <hi>Margaret,</hi> daughter of <hi>Andrew Foord</hi> of <hi>Cornwall, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</hi> He begat <hi>VVilliam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Regni </seg>4 Edw. 4.</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Domini </seg>1464</label>
                  <hi>VVilliam Oldiſworth</hi> married the daughter of <hi>Nicholas Read</hi> of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>von-ſhire, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</hi> By whom he had <hi>Maurice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Regni </seg>3 Rich. 1.</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Domini </seg>1483</label>
                  <hi>Maurice Oldiſworth</hi> his wife was <hi>Iane,</hi> daughter and <hi>Heireſs</hi> unto <hi>Iohn Sydenham</hi> of <hi>Somerſet</hi>-ſhire <hi>
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr>.</hi> Their ſon was <hi>Thomas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Regni </seg>8 Hen. 22.</label>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anno Domini </seg>1531</label>
                  <hi>Thomas Oldiſworth</hi> married a daughter of <hi>Morgan</hi> of <hi>Pennicoyd</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Monmouth</hi>-ſhire, by whom he was Father of <hi>Nicholas.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95939:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas Oldiſworth</hi> having married <hi>Marjo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> daughter of <hi>Davis</hi> of the city of <hi>Glouc.</hi> had by her <hi>Edward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward Oldiſworth</hi> was in <hi>Q. Maries</hi> daies a <hi>Colonel</hi> in <hi>Flanders:</hi> In <hi>Q. Elizabeths</hi> daies he married <hi>Tace,</hi> daughter to <hi>Arthur Porter</hi> of <hi>Newark</hi> in the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Glouc. <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </hi> Their ſon was <hi>Arnold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arnold Oldiſworth,</hi> Clerk of the <hi>Hanniper,</hi> married <hi>Lucie,</hi> daughter and Co-heireſs of <hi>Francis Baxtu,</hi> Treaſurer to <hi>Mary Quen</hi> of <hi>Scotland.</hi> By <hi>Lucie</hi> he had <hi>Edward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward Oldiſworth</hi> of <hi>Bradley</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Wotten</hi> under <hi>Edge</hi> in the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Glouc. <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </hi> married <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the eldeſt daughter of <hi>George Masters</hi> of <hi>Ciren-Cester</hi> in the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> afore ſaid, <hi>Eſquire.</hi> Their only ſon was <hi>Robert:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Oldiſworth</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Bradley</hi> in the ſaid Pariſh of <hi>VVotton</hi> under <hi>Edge, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  </hi> took to wife <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> daughter of <hi>William Clotterbook</hi> of <hi>Kingsſtanely</hi> in the <hi>County</hi> of <hi>Glouc.</hi> Gent. and had iſſue <hi>VVilliam.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95939:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Oldiſworth</hi> (the <hi>only child</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſaid <hi>Robert Oldiſworth,</hi> or <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his wife, had) was buried <hi>Aug.</hi> 31. 1674 both before he was <hi>married,</hi> and before he was full 21 yeares old.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Good Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>The more <hi>inferiour</hi> this ſlender <hi>Stemm</hi> is unto the generous <hi>Croft</hi> of <hi>Crofts Caſtle;</hi> the more <hi>numerous</hi> thoſe <hi>weeping eyes</hi> were, which I then beheld when the laſt <hi>Branch</hi> of this <hi>Stock</hi> was untimely <hi>cutt off;</hi> And (above all this) the more <hi>narrowly</hi> I <hi>ſearch into</hi> the <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude</hi> of <hi>ſorrows</hi> which I am apt to imagine <hi>Abraham,</hi> the <hi>Friend</hi> of God, <hi>wrestled</hi> with; The <hi>greater Impreſsion</hi> abideth <hi>engraven</hi> upon <hi>my heart,</hi> while (with <hi>true joy</hi> and <hi>much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi>) I frequently <hi>ruminate</hi> how tender a <hi>mercy</hi> the <hi>Preſerver of men</hi> dayly <hi>vouchſafeth</hi> both unto my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Hereford,</hi> and unto your <hi>Ladiſhip,</hi> in <hi>continuing</hi> the <hi>Life,</hi> and in <hi>proſpering</hi> the <hi>daies</hi> of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Herbert Crofts,</hi> your <hi>Iſaac.</hi> To <hi>bury</hi> that <hi>Heir</hi> which is an <hi>only Son,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95939:5"/> to <hi>mourn</hi> for ſuch an <hi>only Son,</hi> as is an <hi>only child,</hi> is (I ſee) A <hi>two-edged</hi> Woe! Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, <hi>by Faith</hi> the <hi>Father of the Faithful</hi> duel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the <hi>Father of the Faithfull</hi> vanquiſhed, <hi>even</hi> this <hi>Triall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Madam,</hi> If either my <hi>conjectures</hi> concerning <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>temptations,</hi> or any <hi>Deſcant</hi> of mine upon his <hi>exemplarie</hi> faith, can aſſiſt your Ladiſhips <hi>growing in grace and in the knowledg of our</hi> Lord <hi>and</hi> Saviour IESVS CHRIST; I ſhall willingly <hi>ſacrifice</hi> this <hi>Sermon</hi> to <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> yea, <hi>I ſhall bleſs God</hi> for <hi>granting</hi> the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Good Ladiſhips humbly devoted GILES OLDISWORTH.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95939:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95939:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95939:7"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>To the Vertuous</hi> Mrs. <hi>BRDGET THORP,</hi> VVidow.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>BRing her forth that ſhe may be burnt:</hi> When <hi>What paper</hi> I now <hi>expoſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.24.</note> I two years ſince <hi>raſhly condemned</hi> unto the <hi>Preſse,</hi> ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>unjuſt Judge,</hi> sa <hi>Judah</hi> was, was I. <hi>Dear Cousin,</hi> I will not ſay that a <hi>Gift</hi> in your <hi>Boſom</hi> did <hi>corrupt</hi> my <hi>Judgment,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 2. 1674.</note> for then your <hi>Purſe</hi> would <hi>pay for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>truth</hi> is, to have me at that time <hi>paſſe</hi> that <hi>ſentence,</hi> you <hi>were not;</hi> to have me now <hi>execute</hi> that <hi>ſentence,</hi> you <hi>are,</hi> the <hi>importunate widow</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me <hi>ceaſe</hi> to <hi>honour</hi> ſuch as are <hi>Widows indeede,</hi> if I do not <hi>from my heart</hi> reverence and <hi>highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme</hi> you, for You <hi>glorifie God:</hi> Whom I ſhould <hi>diſhonour,</hi> ſhould I <hi>conceal</hi> that it is for <hi>His ſake,</hi> and onely for <hi>His ſake,</hi> that you <hi>require</hi> this <hi>Sermon</hi> from</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt <hi>obliged Servant,</hi> and ever <hi>thankful Kins-man</hi> GILES OLDISWORTH.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="Scriptural_passage">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95939:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Gen. XXII.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>(a) 1.</hi> ANd it came to paſſe after theſe things, that God did tempt <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſaid unto him, <hi>Abraham:</hi> And he ſaid, Behold <hi>here</hi> I <hi>am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>(b) 2</hi> And he ſaid, Take now thy Son, thine only Son <hi>Iſaac, whom thou</hi> lovest, and get thee into the land of <hi>Moriah;</hi> and offer him there for a burnt offering upon one of the Mountains which I will tell thee of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(c) 3</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> roſe up early in the Morning, and ſadled his Aſſe, and took two of his young men with him, and <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Son; and clave the wood for the burnt offering, and roſe up, and went unto the place of which God had told him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(d) 4</hi> Then on the third day <hi>Abraham</hi> lifted up his eyes, and ſaw the place afarr off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(e) 5</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid unto his young men, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide you here with the Aſſe; and I and the lad will go yonder and worſhip, and come again to you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(f) 6</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> took the wood of the burnt offering, and laid it upon <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Son, and he took the fire in his hand, and a Knife; and they went both of them together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(g) 7</hi> And <hi>Iſaac</hi> spake unto <hi>Abraham</hi> his father, and ſaid, My father; and he ſaid, Here am I, my Son. And he ſaid, Behold the fire and the wood; but where is the lamb for a burnt-offering.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(h) 8</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, My Son, God will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide himſelfe a lamb for a burnt offering: So they went both of them together.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95939:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>(i) 9</hi> And they came to the place which God had told him of, and <hi>Abraham</hi> built an altar there, and laid the wood in order; and bound <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Son, and laid him on the altar upon the wood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(k) 10</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> ſtretched forth his hand, and took the Knife to ſlay his Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(l) 11</hi> And the Angel of the Lord called unto him, out of Heaven, and ſaid, <hi>Abraham, Abraham,</hi> And he ſaid, Here <hi>am</hi> I.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(m) 12</hi> And he ſaid, Lay not thy hand upon the lad, neither do thou any thing unto him: for now I know that thou fearest God, ſeeing thou haſt not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held thy Son, thine onely <hi>Son,</hi> from me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(n) 13</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> lifted up his eyes, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and behold, behind <hi>him</hi> a Ram caught in a thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket by his horns: And <hi>Abraham</hi> went, and took the Ram, and offered him up for a burnt offering, in the ſtead of his Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(o) 14</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> called the name of that place <hi>Jehovah-jireth:</hi> as it is ſaid <hi>to</hi> this day, In the Mount of the Lord it ſhall be ſeen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95939:8"/>
            <head>THE FATHER OF THE FAITHFULL TEMPTED.</head>
            <div n="Hebrews 11" type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Hebr. XI.XVII.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>By faith <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he was tempted, offered up <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T what time this <hi>Epistle</hi> was written unto theſe <hi>Hebrew Converts,</hi> theſe <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Converts</hi> did (as <hi>at this inſtant</hi> many of us do) endure<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr</hi> 10.32.</note> a <hi>great fight of afflictions?</hi> So great a <hi>Fight of afflictions</hi> they now endured, that, as all of us, ſo moſt of them had confeſſedly<note n="(q)" place="margin">36:</note> 
                  <hi>need of patience:</hi> Such <hi>need of patience</hi> they now had, that the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of this <hi>Epistle,</hi> whoſoever he was, <hi>opportunely</hi>
                  <note n="(r)" place="margin">35.</note> 
                  <hi>preſſeth</hi> them in <hi>the ſame words</hi> where with <hi>I beſeech</hi> you <hi>"Cast not away your Confidence.</hi> And, that <hi>cast a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their confidence</hi> they might not, with <hi>the cords of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95939:9"/> a man,</hi> even with <hi>a three-fold cord,</hi> he <hi>endeavoureth</hi> to <hi>wind up</hi> their <hi>hearts</hi> unto <hi>a stedfaſtneſse of Faith.</hi> For.</p>
               <p>Firſt, from <hi>Habak.</hi> 2.4. he bringeth to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, how (they were not now to learn) that<note n="(s)" place="margin">38.</note> 
                  <hi>the just</hi> ſhould <hi>live by faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next he <hi>defineth</hi> what <hi>faith</hi> is: ſaith he<note n="(t)" place="margin">17.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith is the ſubstance</hi> (the confident expectation) <hi>of things hoped For:</hi> The things which are not ſeen are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and <hi>Faith is the evidence</hi> (the conviction) <hi>of things not ſeen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, to <hi>declare</hi> what faith can do, he in this XI. CAP. <hi>repeateth</hi> what faith <hi>hath done.</hi> Saith he.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>V.</hi> 4. <hi>By faith</hi> Abel <hi>offered a</hi> more coſtly <hi>Sacrifice then</hi> Cains was.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>V.</hi> 5. <hi>By faith</hi> Enoch ſo <hi>pleaſed God,</hi> that <hi>God took him</hi> from Earth to Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>V.</hi> 7. Then when the <hi>whole world</hi> deſpiſed the <hi>fore-warnings</hi> of God, <hi>By faith</hi> Noah was ſo <hi>moved with fear</hi> of the <hi>Flood</hi> to come, that (for himſelfe, and for his familie) he <hi>prepared</hi> an <hi>Ark of refuge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was through a <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>truth</hi> of Gods <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> that <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he was <hi>thereunto called, v.</hi> 8. <hi>forſook his</hi> own <hi>Countrie, v.</hi> 9. <hi>ſojourned in a</hi> ſtrange <hi>Land;</hi> and here <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>offered</hi> up Iſaac.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:95939:9"/>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Hebr. <hi>11.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>By faith <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he was tempted, offered up <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>THis <hi>uſeful Obſervation</hi> immediately <hi>releiveth</hi> us with three <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> comforts,</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>The one, <hi>Abraham</hi> was tempted.</item>
                     <item>The other, <hi>When</hi> Abraham <hi>was tempted he offered up</hi> Iſaac.</item>
                     <item>A third, <hi>When</hi> Abraham <hi>offered up</hi> Iſaac, he <hi>offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up</hi> Iſaac <hi>by Faith.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <div type="observation">
                  <head>Of the laſt of theſe firſt.</head>
                  <p>BY faith—By the <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>benefit</hi> which he made of his <hi>faith;</hi> By the <hi>good fight of faith</hi> which He <hi>fought.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Abraham <hi>fighting</hi> every <hi>affliction</hi> which did <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault</hi> him, and <hi>overcoming</hi> every <hi>affliction</hi> which he <hi>fought.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Offered up</hi> Iſaac— had (although with <hi>much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict</hi>) the <hi>patience</hi> and the <hi>power</hi> to <hi>offer up</hi> Iſaac (1) <hi>upon the Altar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dub:</hi> Since it is ſaid (m) <hi>Now Know I that thou feared God,</hi> It ſhould ſeeme <hi>Abraham</hi> did <hi>offer</hi> up <hi>Iſaac,</hi> not <hi>by faith,</hi> but <hi>through feare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Solut:</hi> You find no <hi>repugnance</hi> between the <hi>feare</hi> there <hi>applauded,</hi> and the <hi>faith</hi> here <hi>extolled:</hi> For example,<note n="(u)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7.</note> 
                     <hi>By faith</hi> Noah <hi>moved with feare</hi> — As a <hi>prudent fear</hi> was the <hi>effect</hi> of that, ſo a <hi>filial feare</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95939:10"/> was the <hi>fruit</hi> of this <hi>Patriarks faith.</hi>
                     <note n="(x)" place="margin">17.</note> By a <hi>faith moving him to feare</hi> Abraham <hi>offered up</hi> Iſaac.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DUB: Since <hi>(n)</hi> the <hi>life</hi> of a <hi>Ram</hi> was <hi>Sacrificed.</hi> and <hi>(m)</hi> the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> was <hi>preſerved,</hi> Can it <hi>hold true</hi> that <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up <hi>Iſaac?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> It <hi>holdeth true</hi> in every reſpect.</p>
                  <p>1 <hi>Solut:</hi> Beyond the <hi>ſcope</hi> of <hi>this Text</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up <hi>Iſaac</hi> repreſentatively: (ye Know) as in <hi>Sacraments</hi> ſo in <hi>Sacrifices</hi> the <hi>ſign ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying</hi> betokeneth the <hi>matter ſignified.</hi> When in the <hi>ſtead</hi> of his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> he <hi>ſlew</hi> that <hi>Ram, Abraham</hi> did <hi>repreſentatively</hi> offer up the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> in the <hi>life</hi> of that <hi>Ram.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2 <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lut:</hi> Within <hi>this Text.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Theſe words he [<hi>offered up</hi> Iſaac,] are not ſo much an <hi>expreſse affirmation,</hi> as a <hi>Select expreſſion:</hi> To ſhew how <hi>uncouth</hi> a <hi>Duty</hi> this <hi>Patriarch</hi> now <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwent,</hi> it is here <hi>specified</hi> that what Duty he now <hi>underwent</hi> [was <hi>to offer up</hi> Iſaac.]</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In our <hi>Authors</hi> his <hi>large acceptation Abraham</hi> did <hi>offer</hi> him <hi>up.</hi> Our <hi>Author</hi> here <hi>proſecuteth,</hi> not the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Faith:</hi> Now, as in <hi>round numbers,</hi> ſo in <hi>running styles,</hi> it <hi>abundantly ſufficeth,</hi> if what is <hi>curſorily affirmed</hi> be <hi>true in the main.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Our <hi>ready writer</hi> forgetteth not unto whom he <hi>Dedicateth</hi> this <hi>Epistle.</hi> Unto theſe <hi>Hebrews Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95939:10"/> was read <hi>every Sabbath-day:</hi> Tell theſe <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> out of the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that <hi>Iſaac</hi> was <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up;</hi> and, out of the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> theſe <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> will tell you your own <hi>limited</hi> ſenſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. With 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.19. compare 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.5.</p>
                  <p>3. <hi>Solut: Moſes</hi> ſhews how <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Inceptively:</hi> For inſtance: <hi>Gen:</hi> 22. He <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>aroſe and went unto the place of which God had told him;</hi> And yet <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>two daies after</hi> he <hi>ſaw that place afarr off:</hi> How this? <hi>Anſw:</hi> He was <hi>v</hi> 3. beginning to go to that place. <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. <hi>Reuben v.</hi> 21. <hi>delivered</hi> Joſeph <hi>out of his brethrens hands;</hi> nevertheleſſe, <hi>v.</hi> 24. <hi>his brethren</hi> did <hi>cast him into a pitt,</hi> and did <hi>v.</hi> 28. <hi>ſell him into Aegypt. Queſt.</hi> How then was <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> delivered? <hi>Anſw: Reuben</hi> v. 21. <hi>began</hi> to <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> and although the <hi>perſon</hi> of <hi>Joſeph</hi> was not, the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Joſeph</hi> was, through <hi>Reubens</hi> care <hi>delivered.</hi> Thus <hi>Abraham,</hi> he <hi>aroſe</hi> to <hi>offer</hi> up <hi>Iſaac:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon although the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> was not, the <hi>perſon</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> was <hi>offered</hi> up <hi>upon</hi> the <hi>altar.</hi> And that too.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Actually:</hi> The <hi>offering up</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, not a three <hi>houres,</hi> but a <hi>three daies</hi> buſineſſe: in all which ſpace, the <hi>Obedience</hi> of this <hi>Patriarch</hi> ceaſed not, untill his <hi>Duty</hi> firſt ceaſed: For he <hi>ſlew his Son.</hi>—</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Intentionally:</hi> As when this Son was firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>Abraham</hi> had a <hi>purpoſe,</hi> a <hi>full purpoſe of heart,</hi> to give this his Son his <hi>Name</hi> at his <hi>birth,</hi> and to <hi>circumciſe</hi> him at <hi>eight daies old:</hi> ſo now that the <hi>ſame Son</hi> is <hi>demanded,</hi> his true <hi>intention</hi> is to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> him <hi>(d)</hi> at the <hi>third day.</hi> And he did ſo.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95939:11"/>4. <hi>Interpretatively:</hi> When <hi>Jephthah</hi> cauſed his deare child <hi>Judg.</hi> 11. to <hi>v.</hi> 39. <hi>vow the vow of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarite</hi> (he did <hi>v.</hi> 31. compared with <hi>v.</hi> 36, 37.) he did <hi>interpretatively</hi> offer up that <hi>daughter of his</hi> for a <hi>burnt-offering</hi> unto the Lord: So here, <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>oblation</hi> receiveth a <hi>value,</hi> not from the <hi>execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his hands,</hi> for (m) <hi>his hands</hi> were <hi>tied up,</hi> but from the <hi>reſolution</hi> of his <hi>mind,</hi> for <hi>(k)</hi> his <hi>mind</hi> was <hi>ſincere;</hi> even ſo much that the <hi>ſearcher of hearts</hi> made this <hi>construction</hi> of his <hi>ſincerity</hi> (m) <hi>Thou hast not with-held thy Son from me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It followeth, If <hi>with-hold</hi> him the <hi>Patriarch</hi> did not, ſome <hi>temptations</hi> or other lay upon the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>areh</hi> to <hi>with-hold</hi> him. And what <hi>ſort of temptations</hi> this might be cometh next to be <hi>diſ-cuſsed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="observation">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AMong the <hi>Heathens</hi> claſſical <hi>Poets</hi> have <hi>from hence</hi> raiſed <hi>fictions</hi> treading cloſe upon the <hi>heeles</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> it ſelfe; Among the <hi>Jewes</hi> noted <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies</hi> have upon <hi>this ſtage</hi> introduced the tempter, <hi>Satan;</hi> and Him too in a <hi>viſible ſhape;</hi> among us Chriſtians <hi>this</hi> one <hi>Historie</hi> hath <hi>tasked,</hi> if not <hi>over-tasked,</hi> the <hi>elegant quills,</hi> the <hi>curious fancies,</hi> the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king imaginations,</hi> yea and the <hi>profoundeſt Judgments</hi> too, not only of <hi>humane writers,</hi> but even of <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsed Divines;</hi> Among the <hi>inſpired pen-men</hi> of <hi>ſacred Witt,</hi> S. <hi>James</hi> expoſtulateth "<hi>When he offered</hi> Iſaac <hi>his Son upon the altar was not</hi> Abraham <hi>justified by works? Anſw:</hi> Verily he was, and by ſuch as <hi>equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95939:11"/> his <hi>first works</hi> and more! To <hi>forſake</hi> his <hi>native ſoil,</hi> his <hi>own Kindred</hi> and his <hi>Fathers houſe</hi> that he might wander <hi>hither and thither</hi> whither he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>neither did nor might</hi> foreknow, theſe were great <hi>ſelf denials</hi> (theſe!) Yet <hi>of theſe</hi> the <hi>phraſe</hi> is<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8.</note> 
                     <hi>when he was called,</hi> ſo<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.1.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord had ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him,</hi> But now that he is to <hi>ſlay</hi> his <hi>Son,</hi> the <hi>word</hi> in my <hi>Text</hi> is (not <hi>When he was called</hi> but) <hi>When he was tried,</hi> ſo (a) not <hi>God did ſay</hi> to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> but <hi>God did tempt</hi> Abraham.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, of theſe <hi>remarkes,</hi> of theſe <hi>asteriſmes,</hi> which ſo many <hi>ſorts</hi> of <hi>writers</hi> have hereunto <hi>affixed,</hi> of thoſe <hi>Annotations</hi> which the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> himſelf hath ſo <hi>graciouſly</hi> contributed, let <hi>every</hi> one <hi>of us</hi> reap ſome <hi>profit,</hi> ſome <hi>ſeaſonable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,</hi> ſome <hi>Spiritual benefit,</hi> for our <hi>preſent conſolation.</hi> If <hi>Moſes</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.3.</note> turn'd aſide to ſee that <hi>burning buſh,</hi> let us with Him (a) <hi>contemplate</hi> (the <hi>greater miracle</hi> of the two) this (c) <hi>thicket</hi> of <hi>thorns,</hi> this <hi>fierce law</hi> (b) which (e) <hi>troubling</hi> the <hi>Patriarch</hi> on (h) every ſide, within <hi>(i)</hi> his <hi>bowells,</hi> within <hi>(i)</hi> his <hi>heart (k) kindleth,</hi> though not a <hi>conſuming,</hi> yet a <hi>melting</hi> fire. For.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Genesis 22" type="part">
               <head>In GEN. XXII.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>Tempted.</hi>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. By all <hi>circumstances, v.</hi> 2. In <hi>very deed,</hi> And <hi>in truth</hi> from <hi>v.</hi> 2. unto <hi>v. eleventh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>manner v.</hi> 1. <hi>recorded,</hi> In the <hi>matter v.</hi> 2.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95939:12"/> 
                  <hi>joyned,</hi> In the <hi>Duty</hi> from <hi>v.</hi> 2 unto <hi>v.</hi> 11 <hi>performed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſuch <hi>points</hi> as <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>ſharpned</hi> his <hi>trial,</hi> In a <hi>trial v.</hi> 2 made up of <hi>afflictions,</hi> From <hi>v.</hi> 2. to <hi>v.</hi> 11. in <hi>afflictions</hi> big with <hi>temptation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh, <hi>my brethren,</hi> Why ſay we that our <hi>wound</hi> is <hi>incurable,</hi> and that never was <hi>ſorrow</hi> like unto our <hi>ſorrow?</hi> Whereas</p>
               <div n="1" type="verse">
                  <head>In <hi>v.</hi> 1. of <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>After theſe things. Qu; After</hi> what <hi>things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Anſw:</hi> After he was aged almoſt an <hi>hundred</hi> and <hi>thirty</hi> yeares: Alas, he hath more need to <hi>keep his bed,</hi> then <hi>(c)</hi> to riſe before the <hi>day dawn:</hi> His <hi>ſhriveled Limbs</hi> require <hi>ſuccour, rest</hi> and <hi>retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> rather then <hi>terrour, toyle</hi> and <hi>travaile: O for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake</hi> him <hi>not in</hi> his <hi>old Age: Spare</hi> him <hi>a little before</hi> he <hi>goeth hence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Anſw:</hi> After <hi>freſh proſperities:</hi> What he had <hi>heard</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> of the <hi>Chaldees,</hi> that he had found true in <hi>Canaan:</hi> Unto Him the <hi>land</hi> of <hi>promiſe</hi> was a <hi>land</hi> of <hi>performances:</hi> For his ſake God had <hi>reproved Kings,</hi> had <hi>put to flight the Armie of aliens,</hi> had <hi>preſerved Lot,</hi> and <hi>bleſsed Iſaac:</hi> He was <hi>rich</hi> in <hi>cattle</hi> and in <hi>men;</hi> And (what <hi>ſweetned</hi> his <hi>wealth</hi>) he <hi>abounded</hi> in <hi>honour,</hi> for he <hi>was,</hi> and was <hi>esteemed,</hi> a <hi>Prince;</hi> a <hi>mighty Prince:</hi> and (that which <hi>ſweetned</hi> both was) he <hi>enjoyed</hi> both his <hi>wealth</hi> and his <hi>honour</hi> in <hi>quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse</hi> and in <hi>aſſurance.</hi> The <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> in whoſe <hi>bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> he now <hi>quartered,</hi> had <hi>ſought</hi> and <hi>ratified</hi> a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacie</hi> with <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>His:</hi> What <hi>Well</hi> they had <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95939:12"/> taken away</hi> was (upon his <hi>first complaint</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored: Out of it now <hi>sprang</hi> not <hi>waters of stife,</hi> but the <hi>iſsues of peace:</hi> In all that he <hi>did,</hi> in all that he <hi>had,</hi> he was <hi>bleſsed;</hi> ſo <hi>bleſſed,</hi> that for the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip</hi> of his God, he had <hi>planted</hi> a <hi>Grove,</hi> In this <hi>Grove</hi> his God <hi>Alſufficient</hi> he now <hi>adored</hi> as his <hi>Everlasting</hi> God: And, as if this <hi>God of his praiſe</hi> had therefore <hi>lifted</hi> him <hi>up</hi> that he might <hi>caſt</hi> him <hi>down,</hi> it <hi>(a) came to paſſe,</hi> ſodainly as a <hi>whirle wind</hi> it <hi>came to paſse,</hi> that <hi>(a) after theſe things</hi> God did <hi>tempt,</hi> God did <hi>trie,</hi> God did <hi>afflict</hi> Abraham: <hi>He looked for good, but behold evil!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Anſw:</hi> After <hi>new hopes:</hi> It was not now, Lord God, <hi>What wilt thou give me, ſeeing I</hi> go <hi>childleſſe?</hi> Neither was it <hi>O that</hi> Iſmael <hi>might live before thee?</hi> God had ſaid <hi>Sarah</hi> ſhall <hi>beare a Son,</hi> A <hi>Son</hi> ſhe <hi>bare</hi> him <hi>at the ſet time of which God had spoken;</hi> A <hi>Son</hi> ſhe bare unto him <hi>in his old Age!</hi> God had ſaid <hi>Thou ſhalt call his name</hi> Iſaac: Out of <hi>dutie,</hi> rather out of <hi>pure joy,</hi> Iſaac <hi>he is called:</hi> that God may <hi>delight</hi> to <hi>bleſſe</hi> the <hi>babe,</hi> the <hi>babe</hi> is upon the <hi>eight day cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.</hi> The <hi>childe groweth,</hi> the <hi>childe</hi> is <hi>weaned; Abraham</hi> maketh a <hi>feaſt, a great feast.</hi> By the <hi>care</hi> of his <hi>Mother,</hi> by the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of his <hi>Father,</hi> yea by <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie</hi> had from <hi>God himſelfe,</hi> the <hi>Youth,</hi> before he is of <hi>full age,</hi> is <hi>made</hi> and <hi>declared heir, Sole heir.</hi> And now <hi>upon whom are the eyes of the whole houſ-hold of faith, but upon</hi> Iſaac? <hi>In whom ſhall</hi> all Nations <hi>be bleſsed? In whom ſhall be the</hi> ſeed <hi>of</hi> Abraham <hi>be called, but in</hi> Iſaac? Above <hi>twentie five yeeres</hi> had the <hi>life</hi> of this <hi>Patriarch</hi> bin <hi>bound up</hi> in the <hi>life</hi> of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95939:13"/> this <hi>lad.</hi> And <hi>it came to paſse after</hi> theſe <hi>things</hi>— What? <hi>Anſw: Abraham</hi> rueth the <hi>day</hi> of the <hi>year,</hi> and the <hi>hour</hi> of the <hi>day</hi> wherein <hi>Iſaac</hi> was <hi>born.</hi> To conclude.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Anſw:</hi> After that he was <hi>known of God:</hi> He that <hi>inhabiteth the higheſt heavens</hi> had wonderfully <hi>condeſcended</hi> to an <hi>acquaintance</hi> with this <hi>Patriarch:</hi> He had <hi>entred</hi> into a <hi>covenant,</hi> into a <hi>familiaritie,</hi> into a <hi>friendſhip</hi> with this <hi>Father of the Faithfull. Bow the Heavens,</hi> O Lord, <hi>and come down,</hi> Of late <hi>the Lord</hi> did not ſtay for any ſuch <hi>invitation</hi> from <hi>his</hi> friend <hi>Abraham:</hi> It was at <hi>Abraham his Dwellings</hi> that the <hi>Lord God</hi> did <hi>marſquerade</hi> in the <hi>likeneſſe of men,</hi> made himſelfe <hi>no ſtranger, waſhed</hi> his <hi>feete, rested</hi> in the <hi>cool</hi> of the <hi>arbour, eat well,</hi> and <hi>drank well: Abraham</hi> was the onely <hi>favourite</hi> whom the <hi>Lord God</hi> in <hi>his way</hi> toward <hi>ſodom</hi> had made his <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion:</hi> So very a <hi>friend</hi> was <hi>Abraham,</hi> that from <hi>Abraham</hi> God would not <hi>hide</hi> the thing <hi>which he was</hi> there <hi>doing:</hi> And <hi>after</hi> theſe <hi>things</hi> for a <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Lord and Master</hi> to <hi>trie concluſions</hi> upon his <hi>poor Servant</hi>— this is <hi>harſh! Love unfaind, filial feare</hi> and <hi>cordiall friendſhip</hi> would be, not <hi>tried;</hi> but <hi>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted: Peter</hi> will be <hi>greived,</hi> if <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſhall a <hi>third time</hi> aske <hi>Loveſt thou me?</hi> To <hi>queſtion</hi> the <hi>obedience</hi> of this <hi>Patriarch</hi> is, not to <hi>trie,</hi> but to <hi>break,</hi> his <hi>heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted</hi> in the <hi>revelation</hi> (a) <hi>made,</hi> made <hi>unto Him,</hi> unto Him <hi>in the night,</hi> in the night <hi>by God,</hi> by God <hi>speaking,</hi> by God <hi>ſaying Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:95939:13"/>1. Be it that the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> is <hi>predestinated,</hi> the more will the <hi>mercy</hi> (that I may not ſay the <hi>glory</hi>) of the <hi>most high God</hi> ſhew it ſelf in, not <hi>manifesting,</hi> but <hi>concealing,</hi> this <hi>future evill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If, contrary unto the <hi>accuſtomed mercies</hi> of the <hi>wiſe</hi> God toward the <hi>inquiſitive</hi> ſons of <hi>un-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed</hi> man, Gods <hi>predestination</hi> concerning <hi>Iſaac</hi> be <hi>revealed, Tell it not in Beerſheba,</hi> for (ſhould the <hi>Patriarch</hi> know) it would <hi>bring down</hi> his <hi>gray haires with ſorrow to the grave.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. If to the <hi>unhappy ears</hi> of the <hi>ſurpriſed old Father</hi> it muſt come (Prepare him a little:) Give him his <hi>full ſleep,</hi> a <hi>full meal,</hi> and <hi>due ſtore</hi> of <hi>wine:</hi> Place in a <hi>readineſs</hi> about him <hi>Lovers</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> if not to <hi>ſhare</hi> and <hi>divide,</hi> yet to <hi>bewail</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan</hi> his <hi>Woe.</hi> Then (but not untill then) give unto him ſome <hi>eaſy hint,</hi> ſome <hi>warie fore notice</hi> of what will ſeem <hi>ſad news</hi> at the beſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If this be, not to <hi>tempt,</hi> but to <hi>indulge;</hi> if no <hi>company,</hi> nor <hi>Comforters,</hi> may be admitted; <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary</hi> and <hi>forlorn</hi> as he is, let him (by <hi>himſelfe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone) <hi>recieve</hi> the <hi>intelligence.</hi> but let him <hi>receive</hi> it with a <hi>still voice,</hi> let him not <hi>receive</hi> it <hi>over haſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> To <hi>bolt</hi> upon one <hi>over ſodainly,</hi> ſtartleth even then when one <hi>bringeth</hi> a <hi>bleſſing,</hi> how much more when one cometh not to <hi>befriend,</hi> but to <hi>afflict.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. If <hi>ſodainly</hi> and <hi>unexspectedly</hi> the <hi>newes</hi> muſt <hi>affright,</hi> if <hi>in an hour that he is not aware of</hi> the <hi>aged</hi> and <hi>trembling parent</hi> muſt <hi>hear</hi> the <hi>tidings</hi> of his <hi>dear</hi>-ſons <hi>fate,</hi> Mention it unto him in the <hi>day time,</hi> there is in <hi>Day light</hi> ſome <hi>light</hi> of <hi>comfort;</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:95939:14"/> Mention it not in the <hi>night ſeaſon,</hi> in all <hi>Darkneſs</hi> there is <hi>Dread.</hi> If heretofore there fell upon this <hi>faithful Patriarch</hi> ſuch a <hi>horrour</hi> at the <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of the Sun,</hi> a <hi>greater horrour</hi> will <hi>ſeiſe</hi> him now in the <hi>night,</hi> in the <hi>dark night,</hi> in the dead time of the <hi>dark night.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. If, to add to the <hi>diſcomfort,</hi> there muſt be a <hi>dreadfull horrour</hi> upon his <hi>mind</hi> then when he <hi>heareth</hi> his <hi>Iſaac's doom, ſend, I pray thee, by the man whom thou wilt ſend;</hi> by ſome <hi>Cuſhi,</hi> or by ſome <hi>Amalekite,</hi> for <hi>How</hi> diſmall <hi>are the Feete of him that</hi> bringeth bad <hi>errands?</hi> If <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> be a <hi>good man,</hi> King <hi>David</hi> will from <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> exſpect <hi>good tidings:</hi> Such is their <hi>Clemency,</hi> It is by their <hi>inferiour Judges</hi> that <hi>Princes condemn;</hi> their <hi>own lips speake not,</hi> except <hi>pardons.</hi> If therefore any <hi>Enemies Abraham</hi> hath, let one of them be unto him the <hi>black meſſenger</hi> of his <hi>Iſaac's death;</hi> but <hi>let not the Lord speake unto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, leſt he dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the laſt place, As the <hi>Destinie</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> was brought unto <hi>Abraham</hi> in the <hi>horrour</hi> of <hi>Darkneſse,</hi> and, that too, not by ſome <hi>Enemie</hi> or <hi>stranger,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſome <hi>neighbour</hi> or <hi>friend,</hi> no not by ſome <hi>Man of God,</hi> no nor yet by ſome <hi>Angel of the Lord,</hi> but by the <hi>dreadfull</hi> JEHOVAH himſelfe: So</p>
                  <p n="1">1. God who at <hi>Sundrie times</hi> ſpake in <hi>diverſe manners,</hi> ſpake in this <hi>third age of the World</hi> neither by <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim,</hi> nor by <hi>Thummim;</hi> but either in <hi>Dreames,</hi> or in <hi>Viſions:</hi> Oh, not in a <hi>Dreame,</hi> leſt that <hi>feare,</hi> not in a <hi>Viſion,</hi> leſt that <hi>terrifie,</hi> the <hi>Patriarch:</hi> ſuch
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95939:14"/> a <hi>Dreame,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Viſion</hi> as this, will make his <hi>whole head ſick,</hi> and his <hi>whole heart faint.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let not the <hi>good old man</hi> eſpie an <hi>estranged looke</hi> from his hitherto <hi>benigne Lord,</hi> rather let him not <hi>ſee the face of God</hi> at all; for <hi>Who</hi> can <hi>ſee the face of God, and live?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Suppoſe that the <hi>Lord</hi> do indeede <hi>un-cloth</hi> himſelfe of his <hi>majestie</hi> and <hi>terrour,</hi> Suppoſe he ſpeak <hi>face to face</hi> with <hi>Abraham,</hi> as <hi>a man ſpeaketh with his friend;</hi> Nevertheleſſe, <hi>as the caſe now stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> he <hi>in ſo doing,</hi> Will not (as his <hi>manner</hi> was) <hi>confirm</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> this <hi>Holy Father,</hi> but he will (as his <hi>manner</hi> is not) <hi>deterre</hi> and <hi>diſmay</hi> Him, For</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Call thy Daughter</hi> Jo-ruhamah, and <hi>thy Son</hi> Lo-ammi: Call <hi>Na-ommi,</hi> not <hi>Naomi,</hi> but <hi>Marah:</hi> If a <hi>ſignet</hi> on the Lords <hi>right hand Jeconiah</hi> may not be, deal <hi>ſquarely</hi> with him, name him, not <hi>Jeconiah,</hi> but <hi>Coniah:</hi> And if <hi>(a)</hi> God come, not to <hi>bleſse,</hi> but to <hi>tempt,</hi> if he come to <hi>un-Abraham</hi> the <hi>Patriarch,</hi> ſay <hi>(a)</hi> not <hi>Abraham,</hi> but <hi>Abram.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>I have called thee by thy name, thou art mine.</hi> The <hi>favouritie,</hi> as ever, <hi>awaketh, starteth</hi> up, and <hi>with joy,</hi> anſwereth <hi>unto his name,</hi> but <hi>(b) Hope diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed maketh</hi> his <hi>heart ſick.</hi> For.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="verse">
                  <head>In <hi>v.</hi> 2. of <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. IN the <hi>(b) Surprize</hi> of which he <hi>(a)</hi> never <hi>dreamed.</hi> He <hi>(a)</hi> thought to heare not the <hi>dire will,</hi> but the <hi>good pleaſure,</hi> of his <hi>bountifull Lord;</hi> He <hi>(a)</hi> expecteth not a <hi>burden,</hi> but a <hi>bleſſing;</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:95939:15"/> not a <hi>strict charge</hi> but <hi>enlarged promiſes;</hi> not a <hi>bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling command,</hi> but <hi>loving kindneſſes better then life.</hi> Me thinks I <hi>ſee,</hi> me thinketh I <hi>hear,</hi> the <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed heart</hi> of this <hi>ſurpriſed Favourite</hi> (b) <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting</hi> his God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take now</hi> — O bleſſed <hi>poſseſſour of heaven and of earth,</hi> Thou art alwaies <hi>like thy ſelf,</hi> Thou art <hi>alwaies giving!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take now thy ſon</hi> — Which of the <hi>two ſons</hi> whom the Lord hath <hi>graciouſly</hi> given unto mee? Him by the <hi>Bond-woman?</hi> or Him by the <hi>Free-woman?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thine only Iſaac</hi> — The <hi>apple of</hi> mine <hi>eye,</hi> and of <hi>thine eye</hi> alſo, O my God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whom thou lovest</hi>— And, <hi>O most high God,</hi> whom <hi>Thou</hi> loveſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And get thee unto the land of</hi> Moriah—For there <hi>the Lord will command his bleſſings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And there for a burnt offering offer</hi> — Moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably hitherto <hi>this Favourite</hi> fed his <hi>hopes.</hi> But when it (b) added — <hi>for a burnt offering offer Him</hi> — then was <hi>Abraham</hi> tempted!</p>
                  <p n="1">1 What had He <hi>ſinned?</hi> that among all the <hi>inhabitants of Gods earth</hi> He alone ſhould be <hi>ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out</hi> for ſuch a <hi>prodigie</hi> as this? Had he <hi>treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsed</hi> againſt a <hi>Neighbours Wife,</hi> reaſon good then that he ſhould give his <hi>first born for his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, the fruit of his body for the ſin of his ſoul:</hi> But (<hi>bleſſed be</hi> his <hi>God</hi>) He had wrought no ſuch <hi>follie</hi> (hee!) Admit he had, Here after the <hi>ſon</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95939:15"/> Davids <hi>adulterie</hi> ſhall dye a <hi>natural death;</hi> and ſhall the <hi>Son of</hi> Abrahams <hi>integritie</hi> be <hi>haled,</hi> like a <hi>beast</hi> unto the <hi>ſlaughter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Offer him up there</hi> — To whom? <hi>Satan?</hi> He <hi>was a murderer from the beginning:</hi> As for <hi>the God of all fleſh</hi> His <hi>Delight</hi> is, not to <hi>deſtroy,</hi> but to <hi>preſerve,</hi> the <hi>work of his own hands.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Of man ſhall mans blood be required:</hi> Doth God trapan <hi>Abraham?</hi> If <hi>when He ſhew his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> a <hi>mark</hi> was ſet upon <hi>Cain,</hi> ſhould <hi>Abraham</hi> ſlay his ſon, would his God <hi>hold him guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Take now thy Son</hi>— For what, for a <hi>burnt offering?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Behold for a <hi>burnt offering</hi> ſome <hi>Lamb</hi> or <hi>Kid</hi> is <hi>proper:</hi> ſuch a <hi>firstling</hi> the <hi>righteous</hi> Abel <hi>offered up,</hi> and with that ſacrifice the Lord was then <hi>well pleaſed:</hi> Doth he now <hi>forget</hi> to be <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious?</hi> And hath he ſhut up the <hi>bowels</hi> of his <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions? The tender mercies of the wicked are cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell; Are the tender mercies of</hi> JEHOVAH ſo too? Loe, the blood of <hi>bullocks</hi> or of <hi>he goates,</hi> of <hi>Lambs,</hi> or of <hi>Kids,</hi> he doth not now <hi>require;</hi> the <hi>blood</hi> of which the <hi>preſerver of men</hi> is now <hi>pleaſed</hi> to <hi>drink,</hi> is <hi>mans blood!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. As <hi>mans blood,</hi> ſo not the <hi>blood</hi> of ſome <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, rebel,</hi> or <hi>oppreſſor,</hi> not the <hi>blood</hi> of ſome <hi>Cain, Lamech,</hi> or <hi>Nimrod;</hi> but of one <hi>harmleſs</hi> and <hi>blameleſs,</hi> of one <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>just.</hi> It was but in <hi>v.</hi> 32. of <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. that the Lord <hi>inclined</hi> to ſpare a <hi>wicked City</hi> for <hi>righteous perſons</hi> ſakes. Is he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95939:16"/> now for <hi>spareing</hi> the <hi>ungodly,</hi> and for <hi>condemning</hi> the <hi>righteous?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Power out thy wrath upon the</hi> Heathen <hi>which have not known thee:</hi> as for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> he is no <hi>idolatrous Chaldean,</hi> no <hi>prophane Canaanite,</hi> no <hi>un-circumciſed ſinner of the Gentiles;</hi> but a perſon <hi>circumciſed</hi> and <hi>religious,</hi> One who anon asketh <hi>(g) Where is the lamb for a burnt offering?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. He was, as of the ſame <hi>holy profeſſion</hi> with this <hi>Father of the Faithfull,</hi> ſo no <hi>ſtranger, foriener,</hi> or <hi>proſelite,</hi> but a <hi>native,</hi> and this <hi>native</hi> a <hi>domestick,</hi> and this <hi>domestick</hi> a <hi>favourite:</hi> Hereafter <hi>David</hi> may ſpare <hi>Mehpiboſheth,</hi> but no ſuch <hi>libertie</hi> may <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> now uſe.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The perſon <hi>demanded</hi> for a <hi>ſacrifice</hi> is, as a <hi>domestick favourite,</hi> ſo no <hi>kindred afar off,</hi> no nor yet ſome one or other of <hi>Lots inceſtuous offſpring,</hi> no nor any <hi>Daughter,</hi> or <hi>Son</hi> of any <hi>concubine</hi> (for as yet <hi>concubine Abraham</hi> had none) neither yet the <hi>Son</hi> of his <hi>hand-maiden Hagur,</hi> but the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Sarah</hi> his <hi>Wife.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. If the better <hi>Jonathan</hi> deſerveth, the more <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi> he findeth, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſurely die</hi> will <hi>Saul</hi> ſay to <hi>Jonathan:</hi> But <hi>unto</hi> His <hi>Father, Iſaac</hi> was a <hi>Son</hi> as <hi>deare,</hi> as <hi>deſerving.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, <hi>Abſolom,</hi> he was a <hi>Son dearly beloved</hi> of his <hi>Father</hi> yet was not he the <hi>heire</hi> of his <hi>Fathers throne,</hi> the <hi>heir</hi> of <hi>David</hi> was <hi>Solomon.</hi> but, unto <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Iſaac,</hi> is, as a <hi>deare Son,</hi> ſo an <hi>onely heire;</hi> and this <hi>onely heir</hi> is <hi>born</hi> unto his <hi>parents</hi> in their <hi>old Age,</hi> given <hi>beyond hopes,</hi> given by <hi>promiſe,</hi> by the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95939:16"/> 
                     <hi>promiſe</hi> of the ſame <hi>Jehovah</hi> who now ſaith <hi>(b) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him up for a burnt offering:</hi> What was, if this was not, to <hi>tempt</hi> Abraham?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted</hi> as in a <hi>commandement</hi> thus <hi>grevious,</hi> ſo in the <hi>manner</hi> how his God <hi>wordeth</hi> his <hi>Commandement.</hi> Ye know, <hi>bitter pills</hi> would be <hi>guilded</hi> to the <hi>eye,</hi> and <hi>loathſom potions</hi> would be <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred</hi> to the <hi>tast: Burdenſome taxes</hi> are <hi>levied</hi> by <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Names,</hi> and <hi>ſevere Edicts</hi> neede a <hi>gratifying language. Is it not a little one?</hi> ſaid <hi>Lot</hi> of <hi>Zoar;</hi> and, of what he would have the <hi>ſeller</hi> part with <hi>"It is naught, it is naught, will the buyer</hi> ſay. That <hi>pain</hi> is <hi>almoſt past</hi> which is not <hi>fore thought</hi> of; therefore <hi>to him that is afflicted</hi> this <hi>pitie ſhould be ſhowed,</hi> that where every word <hi>woundeth</hi> there <hi>few words</hi> would be <hi>uſed:</hi> words not <hi>aggravating</hi> but <hi>extenuating,</hi> miſeries: Whereas that <hi>form of ſpeech</hi> which God (b) <hi>uſeth</hi> unto his <hi>Patriarch</hi> is (if ye <hi>review</hi> it) unto his <hi>head</hi> a <hi>maul,</hi> in his <hi>ſide arrows,</hi> and in his <hi>Heart</hi> a <hi>Sword.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Take now — No <hi>leiſure</hi> to <hi>deliberate?</hi> No <hi>time</hi> to <hi>prepare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take now thy Son</hi> — Ever the <hi>nearer</hi> the <hi>relation,</hi> the more <hi>cutting</hi> the <hi>ſeveritie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thine onely Son</hi> — Oh ſtabbing! For <hi>pure pitie</hi> that word <hi>onely</hi> would have bin omitted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thine onely</hi> Iſaac — What, <hi>by Name</hi> too?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thine onely</hi> Iſaac <hi>whom thou Loveſt</hi>—No more (except ye would <hi>breake Abrahams</hi> heart) no more. If ye would not <hi>enrage</hi> do not <hi>awaken,</hi> his <hi>greedie</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:95939:17"/> ſorrowes. Do not firſt <hi>draw out</hi> the <hi>bowels</hi> of his <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> unto a <hi>full length,</hi> and afterward <hi>twist</hi> and <hi>torture</hi> them. The <hi>fathers memorie</hi> is <hi>freſh</hi> enough <hi>of it ſelfe,</hi> do not <hi>vex it as a thing that is raw.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Offer up thy Son— thine onely</hi> Iſaac — <hi>thine onely</hi> Iſaac <hi>whom thou lovest?</hi> — Certainly, if <hi>fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> did not, <hi>astoniſhment</hi> did, render the <hi>Patriarch</hi> quite <hi>ſpeechleſſe:</hi> and as certainly, the ſame <hi>vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency</hi> of <hi>anguiſh</hi> which <hi>un-tongue-tied</hi> the Son of <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> when <hi>(dumb as he was)</hi> he found words to <hi>preſerve</hi> his <hi>condemned Father,</hi> might make this <hi>Patriarch,</hi> while he now ſeemeth <hi>speechleſse,</hi> argue the cauſe of his <hi>demanded Iſaac.</hi> 1. Did I not ſay unto thee <hi>Do not thou deceive mee? Was not my request, O that</hi> Iſmael <hi>might live in thy preſence?</hi> 2. Hath God <hi>ſaid,</hi> and ſhall not He <hi>do it?</hi> Hath He <hi>spoken,</hi> and will not He <hi>make it good?</hi> Is he a <hi>man</hi> that his <hi>purpoſe</hi> ſhould <hi>change?</hi> Or the <hi>Son of Man</hi> that he ſhould <hi>lye?</hi> 3. <hi>Hath</hi> He <hi>ſworn</hi> and would he <hi>repent?</hi> Where is the <hi>truth</hi> of his <hi>free</hi> and <hi>frequent promiſes?</hi> of his <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie</hi> and <hi>ſolemn covenant?</hi> In whom ſhall all <hi>Nations</hi> be <hi>bleſſed,</hi> if <hi>Iſaac</hi> muſt <hi>die?</hi> 4. Accompt that God is <hi>able</hi> to <hi>raiſe</hi> him <hi>up</hi> from the <hi>Dead,</hi> yet what <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit</hi> is there in his <hi>blood?</hi> Shall the <hi>Duſt</hi> praiſe thee, O Lord? Shall it <hi>declare</hi> thy <hi>truth?</hi> 5. If the <hi>Lord</hi> will have <hi>ſacrifice</hi> rather then <hi>mercie, ſhall not the</hi> judge of all the Earth <hi>do right?</hi> He who <hi>forbeareth</hi> the <hi>guiltie,</hi> will He <hi>ſlay</hi> the <hi>innocent?</hi> 6. <hi>All Soules are thine:</hi> even the <hi>Soules</hi> of the <hi>righteous</hi> as well as the <hi>Soules</hi> of the <hi>unrighteous:</hi> yet, loe, Can the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſpeak <hi>better things</hi> then the <hi>blood</hi> of <hi>Abel</hi> did?
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95939:17"/> As <hi>Abel</hi> was, ſhall <hi>Iſaac</hi> likewiſe be, a <hi>type, a figure,</hi> of <hi>good things to come?</hi> Or. 7. If the <hi>Lord</hi> (for the <hi>Lord</hi> is a <hi>God</hi> that <hi>weigheth actions</hi>) if the <hi>Lord</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto the <hi>Counſel</hi> of his <hi>good pleaſure</hi>) be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>working</hi> ſome great <hi>myſterie of godlineſse,</hi> Since <hi>Samſon</hi> will not <hi>refuſe</hi> to <hi>interpret</hi> His <hi>riddle</hi> to his <hi>Delilah,</hi> yea ſince the Lord <hi>concealed</hi> not what <hi>flames</hi> of <hi>vengance</hi> he was <hi>bringing</hi> upon <hi>Sodom,</hi> will he now <hi>hide from</hi> Abraham <hi>the thing which he is</hi> now <hi>doeing? Anſw:</hi> He <hi>(a)</hi> will: and becauſe he <hi>(m)</hi> will,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Anſw. Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted,</hi> as <hi>(b)</hi> in the <hi>manner how,</hi> ſo <hi>(b)</hi> in the <hi>place where</hi> this <hi>burden</hi> was <hi>layed</hi> upon him. For <hi>Quest:</hi> whence did he <hi>(c) ariſe,</hi> but from thence where he <hi>rested</hi> all the <hi>last night?</hi> Where did he <hi>lodge</hi> all the <hi>last night,</hi> but in <hi>Beer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba</hi> at his <hi>owne home?</hi> Within <hi>his owne home</hi> Where, except in the <hi>tent</hi> of <hi>Sarah</hi> his <hi>Wife? Anſw:</hi> If there, <hi>Trouble him not, the door is now ſhut, and the wife of his boſome is with him in bed.</hi> True, were he now (while this <hi>agonie</hi> is upon him) as <hi>farr abſent</hi> from His <hi>dwelling place,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Davids cavalires</hi> will then be <hi>distanced</hi> from their <hi>un-concerned fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> when they ſhall (hereafter) <hi>lament</hi> over <hi>Zik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag;</hi> Were He now <hi>(as they will be)</hi> left <hi>alone</hi> in <hi>fields wide</hi> and <hi>open,</hi> he might now (like them) by <hi>himſelfe alone ſecurely lift up his voice in weeping</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he hath no more <hi>power to weepe.</hi> But being now <hi>ſurpriſed</hi> within his <hi>own doores,</hi> even in the <hi>tent,</hi> that I may not ſay in the <hi>boſom,</hi> of his <hi>Wife, Sarah;</hi> Start out of his <hi>ſleep</hi> he <hi>(a)</hi> doth: but ſhould one
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95939:18"/> 
                     <hi>ſigh,</hi> one <hi>ſob,</hi> one <hi>groan,</hi> eſcape his <hi>strangled thoughts,</hi> Imagine ye the <hi>reſult.</hi> His Wife, ſhe would <hi>cling</hi> about his <hi>elbow</hi> "A bloodie Huſband <hi>unto Me</hi> thou art; <hi>Iſaac</hi> would <hi>hide himſelfe among the ſtuffe; Domestick Servants</hi> would mutinie "<hi>Shall Iſaac die who is the Heir of promiſe?</hi> Iſaac <hi>ſhall not die.</hi> In ſhort, His own <hi>trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bands</hi> would <hi>ariſe</hi> in <hi>armes</hi> againſt <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> as againſt a <hi>Fanatick!</hi> To conclude, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his <hi>Obedience toward his God</hi> he muſt <hi>frustrate</hi> (and <hi>frustrate</hi> his <hi>Obedience toward his God,</hi> he will not:) elſe, being in <hi>bitterneſs for his only Son,</hi> for his <hi>only Son</hi> he <hi>dareth</hi> not <hi>weep;</hi> no not for his only <hi>Iſaac.</hi> Upon <hi>Benjamins</hi> neck <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> ſhall <hi>pleaſe himſelf</hi> in <hi>weeping;</hi> the <hi>bowels</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> yern, upon <hi>Iſaac's</hi> neck he may not <hi>weep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted</hi> in the <hi>No time</hi> (b) given. The <hi>daughter</hi> of <hi>Jephthah,</hi> ſo God will order it, ſhall go <hi>childleſs among Women;</hi> a <hi>joyful mother</hi> of <hi>children,</hi> a happy mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhe ſhall not be: nevertheleſs, this <hi>indulgence</hi> her <hi>tender fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> may <hi>grant,</hi> he may <hi>ſafely</hi> give unto her f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll <hi>two months</hi> ſpace, and therein to <hi>bewail</hi> and <hi>celebrate</hi> her <hi>Virgin life,</hi> before ſhe be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally <hi>conſecrated</hi> a <hi>Nunn,</hi> a <hi>Vestal,</hi> a <hi>Votarie</hi> to her God. But, as for the <hi>Father</hi> of Iſaac, He muſt <hi>ſeize,</hi> he muſt <hi>apprehend,</hi> he muſt <hi>take</hi> his <hi>Iſaac</hi> not <hi>two months</hi> hence but <hi>preſently.</hi> Where it is ſaid unto him (b) <hi>Take thy ſon,</hi> there
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95939:18"/> it is ſaid unto him (b) <hi>Take thy ſon now.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Whither</hi> muſt he <hi>take</hi> Him?</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Anſw:</hi> Not unto the <hi>tent</hi> of his <hi>abode,</hi> for there he might have <hi>ruſhed</hi> upon, have <hi>gulped</hi> down, and <hi>irrevocably</hi> have <hi>executed</hi> the <hi>unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Duty,</hi> ere ever his <hi>more conſiderate heart</hi> had given place unto the <hi>recoilings</hi> of his <hi>fatherly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions, Loving-Kindneſſes,</hi> and <hi>affections.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Neither might (that) <hi>neighbouring grove</hi> be the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of his <hi>ſons death:</hi> for <hi>there</hi> he might have called in <hi>aid.</hi> But:</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Anſw.</hi> He was to <hi>take</hi> his <hi>ſon</hi> unto a <hi>place</hi> (d) <hi>afarr off,</hi> which place, mount <hi>Moriah</hi> by name, was above <hi>forty miles</hi> diſtant from <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> which <hi>forty miles</hi> were; in this <hi>winterly ſeaſon,</hi> unto the <hi>feeble Knees,</hi> and <hi>languiſhing Spirits,</hi> of <hi>heavie hearted Abraham,</hi> little leſs (d) then <hi>three daies journey:</hi> During a <hi>great part</hi> of which <hi>three daies,</hi> to <hi>speake,</hi> was to <hi>betray</hi> his <hi>grief;</hi> to be <hi>ſilent,</hi> was to breed <hi>ſuspicion;</hi> to <hi>stand still,</hi> was <hi>diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience;</hi> to <hi>return back,</hi> was <hi>rebellion;</hi> and to <hi>go forward,</hi> was <hi>death!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Anſw: Get thee into the land of</hi> Moriah <hi>unto one of the mountains which</hi> (b) <hi>I will tell thee of;</hi> How ſhall he get thither? The ſame <hi>Viſion</hi> which (a) <hi>disturbed</hi> his <hi>firſt</hi> nights <hi>rest,</hi> will <hi>theſe</hi> next <hi>two nights</hi> hold his eyes <hi>wakeing;</hi> or if <hi>ſlumber</hi> he doth, his very <hi>ſhuntings</hi> will <hi>affright</hi> him; How can a <hi>dejected, craſie, aged,</hi> perſon <hi>travail,</hi> if he wanteth both <hi>ſleep</hi> and <hi>ſuſtenance?</hi> He can
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95939:19"/> eat no <hi>food,</hi> except <hi>bread</hi> of <hi>affliction;</hi> and he more <hi>heartily feedeth</hi> upon his <hi>griefes,</hi> then upon <hi>that.</hi> I dare not ſay he <hi>mingleth</hi> his <hi>drink</hi> with <hi>teares,</hi> for <hi>theſe</hi> he <hi>ſuppreſſeth;</hi> In the ſtead of <hi>weeping openly,</hi> he <hi>bleedeth inwardly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and <hi>no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veil,</hi> ſeeing <hi>every step</hi> between <hi>Beer-ſheba</hi> and mount <hi>Moriah</hi> preſſeth ſo <hi>heavily</hi> upon his <hi>droop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirits Father</hi> ſaid the (g) <hi>ſecure</hi> lad, <hi>Where is a Lamb for the burnt offering?</hi> Nigh <hi>at hand</hi> (thought the <hi>Father</hi>) but he <hi>durst not ſay ſo.</hi> He was <hi>glad</hi> to <hi>pluck up</hi> his <hi>Spirits,</hi> when with a <hi>ſorrowful heart</hi> (I wiſſe) he <hi>happily</hi> replied (h) <hi>God will provide himſelf a lamb, my ſon. Hungry and thirsty his ſoul fainting in him,</hi> upon <hi>naked moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> in <hi>bleak weather ſlowly</hi> and <hi>mournfully</hi> he <hi>laggeth on,</hi> glad if he might be <hi>priviledged</hi> to <hi>sprinkle</hi> the <hi>ground</hi> with <hi>teares,</hi> and his <hi>head</hi> with <hi>Aſhes,</hi> but he may not thus <hi>mitigate</hi> his <hi>afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> When, after <hi>many,</hi> and <hi>many</hi> a <hi>weariſom ſtep,</hi> he long at the laſt (d) <hi>ſaw the place afarr off,</hi> much more when he (i) <hi>came</hi> quite <hi>to it,</hi> then, more then ever, he <hi>fixed</hi> his <hi>farewel eye</hi> upon his now <hi>ſhort-liv'd Iſaac;</hi> And the more he now <hi>fixed</hi> his <hi>eye</hi> upon his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the more did his <hi>eye</hi> now <hi>affect</hi> his <hi>heart:</hi> But more (by <hi>many degrees</hi> more) was his ſad and mournfull <hi>heart</hi> pittifully <hi>greived</hi> then when he (k) <hi>stretched forth his hand,</hi> and <hi>took</hi> the <hi>Knife!</hi> For</p>
                  <p n="6">6 <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted</hi> as in the <hi>place appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated</hi> to this <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> ſo in the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to be <hi>offered
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95939:19"/> up.</hi> The <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to be <hi>offered up</hi> was <hi>(b)</hi> a <hi>burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering:</hi> and this (ye know) required <hi>(f)</hi> as well <hi>fire,</hi> as a <hi>Knife.</hi> This <hi>burnt offering</hi> was <hi>(k)</hi> firſt to be <hi>ſlain,</hi> and then <hi>(i)</hi> to be <hi>conſumed</hi> with <hi>fire.</hi> I ſay again.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſaac</hi> was (1) as <hi>first</hi> to be <hi>bound,</hi> and <hi>then</hi> to be <hi>layed</hi> over the <hi>altar</hi> upon the <hi>wood,</hi> ſo firſt to be <hi>ſlain</hi> with a <hi>Knife,</hi> and <hi>then</hi> to be <hi>burnt.</hi> A <hi>crueltie</hi> it will be to <hi>cutt</hi> the <hi>throat</hi> of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> but the <hi>inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie</hi> ceaſeth not here: for, when his <hi>throat</hi> is <hi>cutt,</hi> then muſt his <hi>body,</hi> his <hi>whole body,</hi> be <hi>burned, wholy burned,</hi> to <hi>aſhes,</hi> Sirs, if this be that <hi>death</hi> which <hi>Iſaac</hi> is to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> ſay I, <hi>Let me not ſee the death of the Lad.</hi> But (to make the <hi>catastrophe</hi> yet, more <hi>tragical!</hi>) His <hi>Father</hi> muſt <hi>ſee it:</hi> And yet is this <hi>ſigh,</hi> this <hi>prodigious Sight</hi> but the <hi>least</hi> of his <hi>trialls.</hi> For</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted</hi> as in the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> (b) <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned,</hi> ſo in the <hi>ſacrificer</hi> (b) <hi>ordained. Iſaac</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> He is to be the <hi>ſacrifice; Abraham</hi> the <hi>father,</hi> He is to be the <hi>ſacrificer!</hi> 1. If <hi>Iſaac</hi> muſt indeed be <hi>offered up</hi> for a <hi>burnt offering,</hi> let ſome <hi>un-concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned stranger,</hi> or other, be <hi>hired</hi> to be the <hi>ſacrificing Priest.</hi> 2. If by a <hi>strange hand</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> may not <hi>die,</hi> Order ſome <hi>meane out</hi> Servant to give the <hi>deaths wound.</hi> 3. If no <hi>inferiour Servant</hi> may, let <hi>Eleazar</hi> the <hi>Steward, undergoe</hi> this <hi>ſervitude.</hi> 4. If <hi>Eleazar</hi> may not, O let <hi>Iſhmael</hi> be <hi>forced</hi> upon the <hi>Dutie.</hi> 5, Let any <hi>hand</hi> whatſoever, rather then the <hi>hand</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelfe, <hi>binde</hi> and <hi>ſlay</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Abraham.</hi> But</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:95939:20"/>
                  <p>Who may ſay unto God, <hi>What doest thou? Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> muſt <hi>(b) apprehend, Abraham</hi> muſt <hi>(c) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, Abraham</hi> muſt <hi>(f) burden, Abraham</hi> muſt <hi>(i) binde, Abraham</hi> can not <hi>(k) refuſe</hi> to <hi>ſlay, Abraham</hi> can not, <hi>refuſe</hi> to <hi>burn</hi> to <hi>aſhes,</hi> his <hi>Son,</hi> his <hi>onely Son,</hi> his <hi>onely Iſaac,</hi> his <hi>onely Iſaac</hi> whom <hi>he loveth!</hi> Even ſo much that</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2-11" type="verses">
                  <head>From <hi>v.</hi> 2. unto <hi>v.</hi> 11. of <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN <hi>the multitude of thoughts within</hi> Him, 1. While he 1. <hi>ariſeth</hi> ſo <hi>early</hi> 2. <hi>Sadleth</hi> the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> 3. <hi>clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth</hi> the <hi>Wood,</hi> 4. calleth aſide <hi>two</hi> and but <hi>two young men,</hi> and 5. with them <hi>draweth</hi> his <hi>Iſaac</hi> out of <hi>doores.</hi> 2. While he <hi>(c)</hi> conſulteth <hi>hast</hi> and <hi>privacie;</hi> for why elſe did he himſelfe both <hi>Saddle</hi> the <hi>Aſse,</hi> and <hi>cleave</hi> the <hi>Wood?</hi> 3. While <hi>indispoſed</hi> and <hi>enfee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled</hi> as he was) he <hi>(c) began</hi> and <hi>continued</hi> his <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly</hi> (that I may not ſay his <hi>fatal) journey.</hi> 4. When by ſome <hi>undoubted ſignall,</hi> I mean, by ſome <hi>cloud</hi> teſtifying <hi>Gods preſence,</hi> or rather by ſome <hi>pillar of fire;</hi> or rather by ſome <hi>new appearing Starr</hi> he was <hi>(c) told of,</hi> and therefore <hi>(d) ſaw,</hi> the <hi>place</hi> afar <hi>off.</hi> 5. While for reaſons but <hi>too two well know unto himſelfe,</hi> he left his two young men <hi>(e)</hi> behind him, 6. All the while that his <hi>Son</hi> was <hi>(f) carrying</hi> the <hi>Wood,</hi> and that he himſelfe was <hi>(f)</hi> carrying the <hi>Fire</hi> and the <hi>Knife.</hi> 7. While he <hi>(i)</hi> 1. <hi>built</hi> the <hi>altar,</hi> 2. upon it laied the <hi>Wood</hi> in <hi>order,</hi> 3. <hi>bound</hi> his <hi>Son,</hi> 4 <hi>laied</hi> his <hi>Son</hi> over the <hi>altar</hi> upon the <hi>Wood,</hi> 5.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95939:20"/> When he <hi>took</hi> the <hi>Knife;</hi> and 6. <hi>Sretched</hi> forth his <hi>hand,</hi> his <hi>trembling hand,</hi> to <hi>ſlay</hi> his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> his onely <hi>Iſaac:</hi> In all which <hi>tranſ-actions,</hi> unto the <hi>unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly-willing</hi> Father of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> every <hi>new occurrence</hi> could be no leſſe then a <hi>new conflict!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted</hi> as well in <hi>Deede</hi> as in <hi>Thought:</hi> He was <hi>afflicted,</hi> if it were <hi>poſſible,</hi> more in the <hi>evils</hi> which <hi>ominouſly attended</hi> theſe <hi>Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> then in theſe <hi>Occurrences</hi> which <hi>confuſedly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed</hi> his <hi>Obedience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>(comparatively)</hi> a <hi>feeble</hi> perſon, a perſon <hi>aged</hi> an <hi>hundred twenty five</hi> yeeres, <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a <hi>sturdie lad,</hi> a lad <hi>aged</hi> about <hi>twenty five</hi> yeeres. <hi>Iſaac</hi> was <hi>(f)</hi> better able to <hi>carrie</hi> all the <hi>Wood</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for a <hi>burnt offering,</hi> then his <hi>Father</hi> was to <hi>bring with him</hi> the <hi>Fire</hi> and the <hi>Knife.</hi> How there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could the <hi>Patriarch</hi> ſingly <hi>by himſelfe</hi> alone <hi>over power, bind,</hi> and <hi>ſlay</hi> the <hi>robustious</hi> youth <hi>Iſaac?</hi> Should the <hi>boy</hi> find <hi>his</hi> own <hi>strength,</hi> ſhould he <hi>deeme</hi> his <hi>caſe desperate, turn again, ſnatch</hi> the <hi>Knife</hi> out of his <hi>Parents</hi> hand, and (of the <hi>two evils</hi>) chuſe rather to <hi>Kill,</hi> then to be <hi>Killed,</hi> Which way could the <hi>heartleſſe, weariſh</hi> old man be <hi>enabled</hi> to <hi>help himſelfe?</hi> Alas, alas, for his <hi>young</hi> and <hi>ſtrong</hi> Son <hi>Iſaac, Abraham</hi> (the <hi>aged</hi>) is no <hi>match;</hi> (no <hi>match</hi> at all!)</p>
                  <p n="2">2. On the other ſide, Grant that <hi>Iſaac</hi> will not <hi>reſist unto blood;</hi> Let him <hi>beyond</hi> all <hi>expectation</hi> moſt humbly ſuffer both his <hi>hands</hi> and his <hi>feete</hi> to be <hi>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>bound;</hi> Imagine him ſo made up of <hi>ſelfe-deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als,</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:95939:21"/> that he becometh <hi>obedient even unto the death.</hi> If what life the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>weake Father,</hi> can not take from the <hi>Son;</hi> that <hi>life</hi> the <hi>ſon,</hi> the <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> ſon, moſt <hi>chearfully layeth down,</hi> Surely, Sirs, the <hi>Scene</hi> is now <hi>changed,</hi> the <hi>unexspected ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs</hi> of the <hi>child charmeth</hi> and <hi>tieth</hi> up the <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>intention</hi> of the <hi>Father:</hi> Had the <hi>boy</hi> bin <hi>stout hearted,</hi> he might by <hi>reſisting</hi> and <hi>strugling</hi> have <hi>warmed</hi> a <hi>constancy</hi> in the <hi>reſolution</hi> of the <hi>parent;</hi> but, ſeeing the <hi>meek child</hi> doth more <hi>quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> then any <hi>Lamb</hi> give up his <hi>throat</hi> unto his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Knife,</hi> Slay him that can for <hi>Abraham:</hi> If cauſe ſo requireth, <hi>Abraham</hi> can <hi>die</hi> in the <hi>ſtead</hi> of his <hi>child,</hi> but <hi>ſlay him</hi> he cannot. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up,</hi> Iſaac? <hi>How ſhall I offer thee up,</hi> my Son? <hi>My bowels are turned within me, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentings</hi> are <hi>Kindled together. O</hi> that <hi>I might dye for thee, my ſon, my ſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Let <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> too <hi>religiouſly determine</hi> that <hi>Jehovah</hi> ſhall <hi>fullfill</hi> his <hi>whole</hi> pleaſure upon them both. Let the <hi>burnt offering</hi> by God <hi>required</hi> be both by the <hi>ſacrificer</hi> and by the <hi>ſacrificed</hi> a <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will offering:</hi> Let <hi>Iſaac</hi> be ſlain, and, being <hi>ſlain,</hi> let him be <hi>burnt</hi> to <hi>aſhes.</hi> An Hour hence, when the <hi>beat</hi> of <hi>zeal</hi> is <hi>inſenſibly cooled,</hi> and when <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affections</hi> do as <hi>inſenſibly Kindle,</hi> View then the <hi>Patriarch weeping for his</hi> only Iſaac, <hi>becauſe he is not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Let him <hi>wipe all teares from</hi> his <hi>eyes,</hi> and let <hi>him wipe</hi> them all away <hi>by Faith;</hi> the <hi>blood</hi> upon his <hi>hands</hi> he cannot ſo ſoon <hi>waſh off:</hi> Loe, a <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95939:21"/> diſtance</hi> hence <hi>two young men</hi> (e) <hi>wait</hi> as wel the <hi>Sons</hi> as the <hi>Fathers return.</hi> Let <hi>Abraham</hi> ſee to it; Should their <hi>blood</hi> ariſe at <hi>blood-guiltineſs,</hi> Should they <hi>in a furie</hi> avenge upon their <hi>old Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> the <hi>death</hi> of their <hi>young Master,</hi> the <hi>aged fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> I <hi>wiſſe,</hi> is but <hi>one</hi> againſt <hi>two;</hi> Eſcape <hi>for his life</hi> he cannot.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Suppoſe that theſe <hi>two young men</hi> will <hi>keep counſel,</hi> if they can; yet will not <hi>Sarah</hi> be ſo ſaid: As for <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> he will <hi>ſuspect</hi> His <hi>turn</hi> to be the next Hardly will any <hi>Subject</hi> deem himſelf <hi>ſafe</hi> within the <hi>juriſdiction</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Prince,</hi> as hath by <hi>vertue</hi> of his <hi>arbitrarie power,</hi> in <hi>a mercileſſe frenzie, ſacrificed</hi> even his <hi>own child.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Give <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>life for a prey:</hi> yet, <hi>if the foundations be caſt down, what</hi> can <hi>the righteous do?</hi> In <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>ſeed,</hi> which <hi>ſeed</hi> is <hi>Christ,</hi> ſhall <hi>all the world</hi> be <hi>bleſſed;</hi> Although <hi>Iſaac</hi> remaineth <hi>childleſs,</hi> in <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhall <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>ſeed</hi> be <hi>called:</hi> Sacrifice <hi>Him,</hi> and out of whoſe <hi>loins</hi> ſhall <hi>come</hi> the <hi>appointed Saviour</hi> of all <hi>mankind?</hi> Verily the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the <hi>hope</hi> of Gods <hi>elect,</hi> the <hi>Expectation</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> are <hi>all three of them</hi> in <hi>vain,</hi> if for a <hi>burnt offering Iſaac</hi> be <hi>offered</hi> up <hi>childleſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. Accompt that God is <hi>able</hi> to <hi>raiſe</hi> him <hi>from the dead.</hi> Let this <hi>Father of the Faithful believe, hope,</hi> and reſt <hi>aſſured</hi> that, out of the <hi>dead aſhes</hi> of his <hi>Son,</hi> not <hi>another,</hi> but the <hi>ſelf ſame Iſaac</hi> whom he <hi>offered up,</hi> ſhall be <hi>raiſed</hi> unto <hi>life</hi> upon <hi>earth;</hi> Grant all this, and more; Nevertheleſs,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95939:22"/> except his <hi>own family,</hi> and with them his other <hi>relations,</hi> believe the <hi>certainty</hi> of this as <hi>truly</hi> as He himſelf <hi>believeth</hi> it, Into what a <hi>strait</hi> is <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> now brought? yea.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Let <hi>ſound believers,</hi> and with them all other <hi>well-wiſhers</hi> make the beſt <hi>interpretation</hi> which they <hi>rationally</hi> can make of this <hi>Patriarch</hi> his <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> yet for an <hi>un-provoked Father</hi> (under a <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>Religion!</hi>) to <hi>embrue</hi> his <hi>own hands</hi> in the <hi>blood</hi> of his <hi>own child,</hi> is a <hi>Fact</hi> ſo <hi>inhumane,</hi> ſo <hi>barbarous,</hi> and (in <hi>this age</hi> of the <hi>world</hi>) ſo <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard</hi> of, that the <hi>bruit</hi> of it will <hi>ſpread farr</hi> and <hi>near;</hi> It will <hi>unavoidably</hi> open the <hi>mouths</hi> of <hi>evil ſurmiſers</hi> to <hi>speak</hi> all <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>Falſhoods</hi> againſt Him both at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>abroad.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. It will <hi>hence forward</hi> be <hi>charged</hi> againſt Him how. 1. It was for no <hi>goodneſs</hi> that <hi>of old</hi> he <hi>fled</hi> his <hi>Country,</hi> and hath <hi>ever ſince</hi> bin <hi>ſhifting places</hi> from <hi>one people</hi> to <hi>another Kingdom</hi> like a meer <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive</hi> and <hi>vagabond.</hi> Neither 2. had he (as <hi>fifty years</hi> ſince he did) ſo <hi>careleſly forſaken</hi> his <hi>own kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> and his <hi>Fathers houſe,</hi> if he had not <hi>then</hi> bin, as he <hi>now</hi> is, <hi>devoid</hi> even of <hi>natural affections:</hi> 3. <hi>Hagar</hi> had a <hi>taste</hi> of his <hi>kindneſs</hi> when he <hi>turned</hi> her <hi>packing</hi> out of <hi>doors:</hi> 4 It did not over much <hi>conſist</hi> with a <hi>conjugal love,</hi> while his <hi>wife Sarah</hi> continued <hi>alive</hi> to take <hi>Hagar</hi> into his <hi>bed:</hi> and 5. there was in him as little <hi>honeſty</hi> as <hi>good nature,</hi> when (to <hi>humour</hi> his <hi>moroſe</hi> wife) He, contrary to the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>nations, diſinherited</hi> his <hi>first born</hi> ſon, <hi>Iſhmael.</hi> In brief, the <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> the <hi>ſobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:95939:22"/> the <hi>gravity,</hi> the <hi>integrity</hi> &amp;c. of <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>whole life paſt</hi> will (by this one <hi>dead flie</hi> in his <hi>Ointment</hi>) be <hi>for ever hereafter</hi> utterly <hi>diſcredited,</hi> to ſay <hi>no Worſe.</hi> He who moſt juſtly <hi>valued</hi> his <hi>good name</hi> above <hi>ſpoiles</hi> by him <hi>taken</hi> in <hi>warr,</hi> muſt now live to be a <hi>ſcorn,</hi> and a <hi>deriſion,</hi> and a <hi>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> amonſt Men. Wherefore, if <hi>Jonah</hi> will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>flie from the preſence of the Lord</hi> then <hi>adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> to be <hi>reputed</hi> a <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> Conſider (I pray you) how <hi>un-ſupportable</hi> a <hi>temptation</hi> will then <hi>cruſh</hi> this <hi>reverend</hi> and <hi>venerable Patriarch</hi> when He (hitherto a <hi>mighty Prince</hi>) ſhall be had in no <hi>reputation,</hi> rather when he ſhall be an <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> and <hi>offſcouring</hi> among men, even the <hi>gazing stock</hi> and <hi>Spectacle</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi> Might <hi>Abraham</hi> be ſuffered to <hi>cutt</hi> as well his own <hi>throat,</hi> as the <hi>throat</hi> of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> might he <hi>give</hi> his <hi>body</hi> to be <hi>burnt</hi> upon his <hi>ſons,</hi> and with his ſons <hi>aſhes intermix</hi> his <hi>own,</hi> this would not be unto him ſo <hi>great a death,</hi> as that <hi>Contempt</hi> will be which the death of his <hi>Iſaac</hi> will every where bring upon Him: That <hi>mark</hi> which was ſet upon <hi>Cain</hi> will not <hi>equal</hi> the <hi>brand</hi> which ſhall be <hi>fixed</hi> upon <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Great</hi> was this <hi>trial,</hi> but <hi>greater</hi> is that which <hi>attendeth</hi> it; ſeeing what <hi>reproaches</hi> ſoever <hi>asperſe</hi> Him, <hi>ſully</hi> the <hi>undefiled worſhip of</hi> his <hi>God:</hi> Look how much you <hi>diſavow</hi> Him, and ſo much you <hi>diſesteem</hi> his <hi>exemplary godlineſs; Blemiſh</hi> his <hi>good name,</hi> and ye <hi>blast</hi> his holy <hi>profeſſion.</hi> Every <hi>ſlander</hi> againſt <hi>himſelf</hi> doth, thorough His ſide, <hi>wound</hi> that <hi>Religion</hi> which He <hi>defendeth.</hi> For
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95939:23"/> 
                     <hi>example,</hi> His <hi>former zeal</hi> will be, by the <hi>blood</hi> of his <hi>Son, diſcouloured,</hi> as if it had bin <hi>diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, hypocriſie,</hi> or what not? By the <hi>aſhes</hi> of his <hi>Iſaac</hi> his late <hi>Devotions</hi> will ſeeme <hi>pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced,</hi> they will <hi>appeare</hi> like ſo much <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie, humour,</hi> or <hi>affectation.</hi> Yea the <hi>puritie</hi> of that <hi>true Religion</hi> which He <hi>countenanceth,</hi> will now be <hi>cenſured</hi> a <hi>worſhip</hi> of his own <hi>invention!</hi> Alas, that every <hi>altar</hi> by Him <hi>erected</hi> in a <hi>thankful remembrance</hi> of <hi>that</hi> God <hi>whom</hi> He <hi>ſerveth,</hi> ſhould <hi>henceforward</hi> be <hi>looked upon,</hi> not as the <hi>perpetual monuments</hi> of the <hi>onely</hi> true <hi>God,</hi> but as <hi>certain arguments</hi> of this <hi>Patriarch</hi> his <hi>ostentation</hi> and <hi>madneſse.</hi> Woe will it be with the <hi>Houſ-hold of faith,</hi> when the <hi>life</hi> of this <hi>parent</hi> and the <hi>Death</hi> of this <hi>Child,</hi> ſhall be <hi>taken up</hi> for a <hi>ſcoffe,</hi> a <hi>taunt,</hi> for a <hi>reproach,</hi> and by-word, for a <hi>ridicule</hi> and a <hi>proverb,</hi> amongſt all the <hi>inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing adverſaries</hi> of <hi>Godlineſse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Review a little how <hi>powerfully</hi> this laſt <hi>trial</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pteth <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>deſist</hi> from <hi>offering up</hi> his <hi>Iſaac.</hi> viz. To <hi>ſacrifice</hi> his <hi>just</hi> and moſt <hi>deſerved Dignitie</hi> and <hi>Eſteem</hi> in the <hi>fate</hi> of his <hi>Son,</hi> to let his <hi>own</hi> Name <hi>periſh</hi> with his <hi>childes Life,</hi> by this one <hi>ſtroke</hi> to <hi>make</hi> himſelfe <hi>of</hi> no <hi>reputation,</hi> the <hi>Patriarch</hi> (in <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> toward his <hi>God) refuſeth</hi> not; could it <hi>stand</hi> with the <hi>reputation</hi> of <hi>Divine Worſhip:</hi> But, ſo it is that, if the <hi>one</hi> ſuffereth, the <hi>other</hi> ſuffereth alſo. The <hi>pure,</hi> the <hi>Holy,</hi> the <hi>unſpotted Worſhip</hi> of the moſt <hi>High God</hi> Will (by this <hi>one ſacrifice</hi> once <hi>offered up</hi>) be even unto perſons <hi>honest, ſober,</hi> and <hi>quiet</hi> an <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> and <hi>ſcandall.</hi> The <hi>ſcandal</hi> that will be <hi>given,</hi> the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95939:23"/> 
                     <hi>Prejudice</hi> that will be <hi>taken</hi> againſt the <hi>Holy Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>glorious</hi> Lord <hi>God,</hi> this (this) is that which <hi>casteth down</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> of this <hi>Patriarch,</hi> while in the <hi>hand</hi> of this <hi>Patriarch</hi> the <hi>ſlaughter-Knife</hi> is <hi>lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There yet remaineth one <hi>triall</hi> unſpoken of, the which in <hi>humane probabilitie</hi> will bring upon the <hi>Father of the Faithfull</hi> a greater <hi>temptation</hi> unto <hi>diſobedience,</hi> then this and <hi>ſome</hi> former <hi>circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> could doe, were all of them <hi>blended together</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one <hi>complicated evil</hi> The remaining <hi>triall</hi> is this.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>obloquies</hi> of them who will <hi>revile Him,</hi> and his <hi>religion,</hi> will fall not ſo <hi>maliciouſly</hi> upon <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> as upon the God <hi>whom</hi> He <hi>ſerveth.</hi> It is <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi> His <hi>will</hi> that his <hi>Iſaac</hi> is <hi>ſlain,</hi> and therefore the <hi>world</hi> will <hi>ceaſe</hi> to <hi>asperſe</hi> Him as if He <hi>delighted</hi> in <hi>cruelties;</hi> neither is it <hi>of his own head</hi> that he <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth</hi> this <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> ſo that he ſhall <hi>not long</hi> be <hi>branded</hi> with an <hi>act</hi> of <hi>will worſhip:</hi> The <hi>burnt-offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> which he <hi>bringeth</hi> he <hi>offereth up,</hi> not of <hi>choice,</hi> but in <hi>Duty:</hi> and the <hi>truth</hi> hereof will <hi>in due time</hi> come <hi>to light.</hi> But herein (as I conceive) herein is the <hi>consternation</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>Spirit:</hi> So long as the <hi>commandement</hi> of his God might abide <hi>concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> ſo long there was not <hi>given</hi> unto the <hi>enemies</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſo <hi>great</hi> an <hi>occaſion</hi> to <hi>Blaſpheme.</hi> On the other ſide, to the deepe <hi>anguiſh</hi> of his <hi>Soul,</hi> the <hi>Patriarch</hi> calleth to mind that ſo ſoon as ever it ſhall be <hi>understood</hi> that the Lord had ſaid unto him <hi>Offer up thy Son,</hi> forthwith <hi>all people</hi> will <hi>open</hi> their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95939:24"/> 
                     <hi>mouths</hi> againſt that <hi>Jehovah</hi> who <hi>laid</hi> upon the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> a <hi>command</hi> ſo <hi>unmerciful,</hi> ſo <hi>ungodly,</hi> ſo <hi>pernicious.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Behold, all other <hi>conflicts</hi> are now <hi>over:</hi> and <hi>all things</hi> are now <hi>readie:</hi> The <hi>alter</hi> is <hi>built,</hi> the <hi>Wood</hi> is <hi>orderly laid</hi> upon the <hi>altar;</hi> By <hi>his</hi> own <hi>Father, Iſaac</hi> is <hi>bound;</hi> and is (for the <hi>eaſe</hi> of his <hi>Father</hi>) by <hi>his</hi> own <hi>ſelfe</hi> placed over the <hi>altar</hi> upon the <hi>Wood:</hi> At the <hi>Fathers feete,</hi> and in the <hi>Fathers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,</hi> the <hi>fire kindleth:</hi> His <hi>Arm</hi> is <hi>stretched forth,</hi> and in his <hi>hand,</hi> the <hi>Knife;</hi> but the <hi>ſuspence</hi> is — If unto the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Son of <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt be <hi>offered up,</hi> What will the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> do unto his <hi>great Name? Anſw:</hi> Who ſo (will <hi>atheiſts</hi> ſay.)</p>
                  <p>Who ſo would be <hi>bound</hi> by <hi>covenant</hi> — to <hi>Live</hi> and <hi>Die</hi> a <hi>stranger</hi> amongſt his <hi>Enemies,</hi> Who ſo, in <hi>Obedience</hi> unto his <hi>God,</hi> would <hi>ſhift</hi> in <hi>tents</hi> from <hi>region</hi> to <hi>region</hi> not having upon earth any <hi>Citie,</hi> or <hi>dwelling place</hi> to <hi>abide</hi> in: He who would be ever <hi>ſeparated</hi> from all his <hi>Kins-folke</hi> and <hi>Relations;</hi> He who would <hi>Worſhip</hi> a <hi>strange God,</hi> a <hi>God</hi> whom the <hi>eye</hi> of <hi>man</hi> never yet <hi>beheld,</hi> a God <hi>inviſible,</hi> a <hi>God</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> (if any ſuch a <hi>handfull</hi> of <hi>people</hi> there be;) a <hi>new-found</hi> God, a God <hi>unknown</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt <hi>prosperous Kingdomes,</hi> and unto the moſt <hi>ſpreading Dominions</hi> of the <hi>World:</hi> Such a one as would <hi>ridiculouſly</hi> and <hi>obſcenely mangle,</hi> and <hi>cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail</hi> the <hi>foreskin</hi> of his <hi>fleſh;</hi> He that can <hi>call</hi> it a point of high <hi>devotion</hi> to be the <hi>prodigious executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of his <hi>dearest childe;</hi> Let him <hi>forſake</hi> the <hi>Gods</hi> of the <hi>Philistines</hi> and of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> let him <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:95939:24"/> the Gods of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> and let him <hi>cleave</hi> unto the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>So then: If unto his <hi>offering up</hi> his <hi>Iſaac</hi> unto his <hi>Jehovah,</hi> we add his <hi>not with-holding</hi> his <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi> from the <hi>contempt</hi> of <hi>blasphemers;</hi> If unto the <hi>ſelf-denials</hi> on which of <hi>neceſſity</hi> he was to <hi>force</hi> His <hi>whole man,</hi> we <hi>annexe</hi> the <hi>evil conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences</hi> which his <hi>ſelf denials</hi> moſt <hi>ominouſly preſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged;</hi> It is as <hi>clear</hi> as His <hi>obedience:</hi> that, when <hi>Abraham offered up</hi> his <hi>Iſaac, Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="objection">
                  <head>OBJECTION.</head>
                  <p>Better it had bin, had neither <hi>God</hi> tempted <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> nor <hi>Abraham</hi> obeyed his God; for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by an <hi>Entrance</hi> was afterwards <hi>ministred</hi> firſt unto the <hi>Heathens,</hi> next unto the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and then unto the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Judah; to <hi>offer up</hi> both <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Daughters</hi> firſt unto <hi>Devils,</hi> next unto <hi>inſenſible Creatures,</hi> and ſoon after (to make the <hi>affront</hi> complete) unto <hi>God</hi> Himſelf.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>REPLY.</head>
                  <p>It is yet to be proved, that if <hi>God</hi> had never thus tempted <hi>Abraham,</hi> then <hi>folk</hi> would never have <hi>offered up</hi> their <hi>Sons,</hi> and their <hi>Daughters</hi> in <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice:</hi> Or ſuppoſe they would not &amp;c. <hi>O</hi> man <hi>who art</hi> thou <hi>that</hi> diſputeſt <hi>against</hi> God? Seeing, as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95939:25"/> the <hi>Extent</hi> of Gods <hi>Commandements</hi> is exceeding <hi>broad,</hi> ſo the <hi>Deſigns</hi> of them are exceeding <hi>deep.</hi> From the <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> was, is, and will be <hi>foreknown</hi> unto <hi>God</hi> what <hi>ſucceſs</hi> ſo ever <hi>did, doth,</hi> or <hi>will,</hi> attend <hi>every</hi> mans <hi>obedience</hi> unto <hi>every</hi> of His <hi>precepts.</hi> By <hi>ways</hi> unto us <hi>unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> he is ever <hi>fulfilling</hi> his hidden <hi>pleaſure,</hi> ever <hi>fetching about</hi> his hidden <hi>Glory;</hi> as for us, Who hath <hi>known</hi> the <hi>mind</hi> of the <hi>Lord?</hi> Or <hi>Who</hi> hath <hi>bin</hi> His <hi>Counſeller?</hi> Leave unto the <hi>infinitely wiſe God</hi> things <hi>ſecret;</hi> Our <hi>concern</hi> is in <hi>things revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. It may be the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſaid unto <hi>Shimei,</hi> curſe <hi>David:</hi> It may be the <hi>just God</hi> had ſaid unto <hi>Satan,</hi> Let the <hi>brats</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> ſee what a <hi>Sottiſh, Apiſh,</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> heart they <hi>cheriſh</hi> in their <hi>graceleſs boſoms.</hi> For <hi>Satan,</hi> that <hi>wicked one,</hi> ceaſeth not to work <hi>evil</hi> out of <hi>good:</hi> but then (our <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge</hi> is) God moſt <hi>Holy</hi> worketh our <hi>good</hi> out of his <hi>evil:</hi> the <hi>poiſon</hi> of this <hi>ſubtile</hi> old <hi>Serpent</hi> is made <hi>treacle</hi> for the <hi>medicinal benefit</hi> of <hi>Gods elect.</hi> Wherefore.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Bleſs thou that God who hath not given thee over unto ſuch <hi>abominable practices,</hi> unto ſuch <hi>helliſh deluſions;</hi> As God hath not <hi>ſorted</hi> thy daies unto the <hi>time</hi> of that <hi>ignorance,</hi> ſo he hath in this <hi>Gospel-age</hi> called thee into his <hi>marveilous light.</hi> He <hi>hath</hi> ſhewed <hi>thee</hi> O man <hi>what</hi> is <hi>good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Let the <hi>Idolatries objected</hi> convince <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> how <hi>fearful</hi> a <hi>Judgment</hi> it is unto a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> when the <hi>rulers</hi> thereof <hi>bear</hi> the <hi>Sword</hi> in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95939:25"/> 
                     <hi>vain.</hi> Wee ſee, Leave a <hi>people</hi> unto the <hi>ſuggestions</hi> of <hi>Satan,</hi> that is, Leave a <hi>people</hi> unto <hi>what</hi> is <hi>good</hi> in <hi>their</hi> own <hi>Eyes,</hi> and they will commit <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſses</hi> deſtructive unto the very <hi>being</hi> and <hi>existing</hi> of <hi>mankind:</hi> Yea they will think that they do God <hi>good Service,</hi> when they are a <hi>ſmoak</hi> in his <hi>nostrils.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 It was but once only that <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted</hi> to <hi>offer up</hi> his <hi>Iſaac</hi> upon the <hi>Altar:</hi> if it be true, that one <hi>ſingle pattern</hi> had ſo <hi>Malignant</hi> an <hi>influence</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeveral <hi>nations</hi> and <hi>ages;</hi> then let every one of us <hi>abstain</hi> from all <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>evil.</hi> A <hi>little</hi> Leaven <hi>Leaveneth</hi> the whole <hi>Lump;</hi> and evil <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,</hi> as well as evil <hi>words,</hi> corrupt <hi>good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Let the <hi>trial</hi> wherewith <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> ſtop the <hi>mouth</hi> (if the <hi>mouth</hi> can be <hi>stopped</hi>) of all thoſe <hi>ſeditious Separatists</hi> among us, who (at this day) <hi>cruelly, diſdainfully,</hi> and <hi>despite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> ſpeake againſt the <hi>righteous;</hi> more eſpecially if (at this day) they <hi>ſubmit themſelves</hi> unto every <hi>ordinance of Man</hi> for the <hi>Lords</hi> ſake. Some <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> and among them ſome <hi>Conformists,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong them ſome <hi>Gospel-Ministers,</hi> be the <hi>endeavour</hi> of their <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>lives</hi> never ſo <hi>ſincere,</hi> yet if <hi>evil</hi> befal, Againſt them forthwith the <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>quils</hi> of theſe <hi>Sectaries</hi> are their <hi>own!</hi> Who is <hi>Lord</hi> over them? Forſooth they <hi>deem</hi> it a <hi>faire advantage</hi> unto their <hi>Sect</hi> and <hi>Partie,</hi> if they can <hi>Libellouſly</hi> and <hi>ſcoffingly</hi> report of <hi>Abraham</hi> that he <hi>spared</hi> no <hi>paines</hi> to have <hi>butchered</hi> his <hi>Iſaac:</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:95939:26"/> Whereas it is not <hi>unknown</hi> unto all the <hi>Churches</hi> that this <hi>preſent Text,</hi> yea and a great part of this <hi>preſent Chapter</hi> inſpireth not the <hi>diminution,</hi> but the <hi>praiſe</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> for <hi>conforming</hi> His <hi>private will</hi> unto the <hi>revealed will</hi> of God <hi>most Holy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion__cont.">
                  <p>But theſe <hi>latter Replies</hi> anticipate mine <hi>intended method;</hi> in as much as, the <hi>three</hi> Uſefull <hi>obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> explained from the <hi>last</hi> to the <hi>first,</hi> I would <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly</hi> applie from the <hi>first</hi> to the <hi>laſt.</hi> For </p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>if <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted,</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. LET the <hi>innumerable afflictions</hi> which this <hi>faithfull Patriarch</hi> ſuffered, for ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after <hi>un deceive</hi> thoſe <hi>ignorant worldlings</hi> who <hi>think hardly</hi> of all ſuch <hi>profeſsours</hi> as <hi>endure tribulation.</hi> When <hi>Chriſts Diſciples</hi> ſaw a man <hi>blind</hi> from his <hi>birth</hi> they <hi>quickly</hi> asked "<hi>Who ſinned,</hi> this <hi>man,</hi> or his <hi>Father?</hi> When, by <hi>clinging</hi> upon St. <hi>Pauls</hi> hand, a <hi>viper</hi> ſeemed to <hi>threaten Death</hi> unto that <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> the <hi>Barbarians</hi> at <hi>Melita</hi> raſhly <hi>concluded "This man</hi> was <hi>ſome murderer.</hi> Uſually the like <hi>opinion</hi> poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the <hi>men</hi> of this <hi>world:</hi> If they ſee one <hi>fallen</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>infamie, povertie,</hi> or ſome other <hi>diſtreſse,</hi> they <hi>begin</hi> to <hi>conceive</hi> hard thoughts againſt ſuch a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian.</hi> But a <hi>believers</hi> comfort is that <hi>Gods</hi> thoughts are not as <hi>Mans</hi> thoughts; With the moſt, he that is <hi>low</hi> in this world is low in <hi>mans</hi> eye; but in Gods <hi>Eye</hi> he is not. <hi>Abraham</hi> had the <hi>honour</hi> (the <hi>peculiar honour</hi>) to be <hi>ſtiled</hi> the <hi>Friend of God,</hi> yet do ye find him <hi>toſſed</hi> from <hi>place</hi> to <hi>place,</hi> a long while <hi>child-leſſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95939:26"/> thwarted</hi> by the <hi>Wife</hi> of his <hi>boſom;</hi> and through her meanes <hi>deprived</hi> of the firſt <hi>bodie</hi> that had made him a <hi>Father,</hi> to witt, of <hi>Hagar;</hi> and of the firſt <hi>Son</hi> that ever he <hi>delighted</hi> in, to witt, of <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> as for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> in Him he was to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> at once the <hi>dearest love,</hi> the <hi>greatest joy,</hi> and the <hi>chiefest hopes,</hi> which the <hi>whole world</hi> could yeild him: Wherefore if this <hi>Friend of God</hi> was thus <hi>humbled</hi> let no <hi>worldling</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>evill</hi> of Gods <hi>favourites</hi> for any <hi>miſeries</hi> which <hi>befals</hi> them in <hi>this life,</hi> much leſſe for any <hi>miſeries</hi> which in <hi>this life</hi> they <hi>draw</hi> upon <hi>themſelves</hi> by <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering</hi> in their <hi>Duties. Behold</hi> we <hi>accompt</hi> them <hi>happie</hi> that <hi>endure.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>O conſider this ye that forget God.</hi> Are any of you ſo <hi>prosperous</hi> that <hi>pride</hi> encompaſſeth you as a <hi>chain,</hi> and ſetteth your <hi>mouth</hi> againſt the <hi>Heavens?</hi> You who <hi>speak</hi> thus <hi>boldly,</hi> and <hi>are</hi> thus <hi>corrupt</hi> this <hi>Hictorie,</hi> and other <hi>Histories</hi> like this, read yee. The righteous <hi>Abel</hi> was <hi>murdered</hi> by his <hi>own brothers;</hi> the righteous <hi>Lott</hi> loſt all his <hi>wealth;</hi> upright <hi>Job,</hi> who more <hi>miſerable?</hi> you <hi>beheld</hi> the <hi>Innocent Iſaac</hi> nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly <hi>eſcaping</hi> a moſt <hi>untimely Death;</hi> And your <hi>eares</hi> have <hi>heard,</hi> and the <hi>eares</hi> of this <hi>aſsemblie</hi> have <hi>heard</hi> with what <hi>reiterated conflicts</hi> the <hi>faithful</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham was <hi>tempted;</hi> If here <hi>upon earth</hi> the <hi>troubles</hi> of the <hi>righteous</hi> are ſo <hi>many</hi> and ſo <hi>ſearching,</hi> can <hi>you</hi> here <hi>upon earth</hi> hope to <hi>eſcape</hi> Gods <hi>judgments? (Be not mercifull,</hi> O Lord, <hi>unto them that</hi> ſin <hi>of</hi> malicious <hi>wickedneſse<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</hi> I appeal unto that <hi>Flood</hi> which in the daies of <hi>Noah</hi> drowned a whole <hi>world</hi> of <hi>tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours,</hi> I appeal unto that <hi>fire</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> which in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95939:27"/> the <hi>daies</hi> of this <hi>Patriarch Abraham,</hi> made <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> the <hi>pictures</hi> of <hi>Hell;</hi> (Within our own <hi>age</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſland</hi>) I appeal unto late <hi>civil Wars,</hi> unto <hi>latter peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences,</hi> and unto <hi>devouring fires</hi> hardly yet <hi>quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> (Within your own <hi>boſoms,</hi>) I appeal unto your ſelf-condemning <hi>conſciences,</hi> that if the <hi>Righteous</hi> are <hi>ſcarcely</hi> preſerved <hi>in</hi> this <hi>Word, in</hi> this <hi>world</hi> it ſhall go <hi>ill</hi> with the <hi>wicked.</hi> If <hi>favourites</hi> are thus <hi>afflicted</hi> here, ſhall <hi>Enemies</hi> continue here <hi>unpuniſhed?</hi> God ſhall <hi>wound</hi> the <hi>head</hi> of his <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> and the <hi>hayrie ſcalp</hi> of <hi>ſuch a One</hi> as <hi>goeth</hi> on <hi>ſtill</hi> in his <hi>trespaſses.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Let <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>temptations</hi> ſpeak <hi>peace</hi> unto many <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who (as if they were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sanctified,</hi> nor <hi>Adopted,</hi> nor <hi>Elected</hi>) are <hi>prone,</hi> alas, to <hi>diſquiet</hi> their <hi>Souls</hi> in the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>trial.</hi> Some <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> although they <hi>believe</hi> that <hi>ſufficient</hi> for the <hi>day</hi> is <hi>every</hi> daies <hi>trouble,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they <hi>grant,</hi> that man <hi>born</hi> in <hi>Sin</hi> is <hi>born</hi> to ſee <hi>ſorrowful</hi> daies; although they <hi>read</hi> that God doth not <hi>willingly afflict,</hi> yea although they fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know that whom the Lord <hi>Loveth,</hi> them he <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sten th;</hi> yet, when the <hi>fierie tryal</hi> tempteth, they <hi>think</hi> that <hi>strange.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1 I beſeech ſuch <hi>dejected Spirits</hi> to <hi>ponder well</hi> that he is the <hi>Penman</hi> of this <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> who was (p) in <hi>bonds;</hi> and that theſe <hi>Hebrews</hi> were then <hi>ſincere converts,</hi> when they were<note n="†" place="margin">
                           <hi>H br.</hi> 10 34.</note> 
                        <hi>spoiled</hi> of their <hi>goods,</hi> and were, by <hi>reproache,</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">33.</note> made a <hi>gazing-stock!</hi> In this cap. XI. It was not <hi>before,</hi> but <hi>after,</hi> that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95939:27"/> they <hi>beleeved,</hi> that they <hi>v.</hi> 38. <hi>wandred</hi> into <hi>deſerts, Mountaines, dens,</hi> and <hi>caves.</hi> Or that <hi>they<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> v.</hi> 37. were <hi>destitute, afflicted, tormented, stoned, tempted, ſlain</hi> with the <hi>ſword,</hi> and (ſome of them) <hi>ſawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder;</hi> that <hi>they v.</hi> 36. had a <hi>greater triall</hi> then any of theſe, <hi>even</hi> the <hi>triall</hi> of <hi>cruell</hi> mockings, of <hi>ſcoffs</hi> which <hi>fetched blood</hi> like a <hi>Sword</hi> in the <hi>bones!</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my <hi>Text, Iſaac</hi> (a <hi>type</hi> of the <hi>ſuffering Jeſus</hi>) ſaw <hi>Death,</hi> although he <hi>felt</hi> it not. And <hi>Abraham,</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of the <hi>Faithful,</hi> was more <hi>tempted,</hi> then <hi>Iſaac</hi> himſelfe was! Unto you I <hi>applie</hi> this, O yee of <hi>little</hi> faith: If, as unto <hi>theſe Saints</hi> (whoſe <hi>Names</hi> are here <hi>written</hi> in this <hi>booke</hi> of <hi>Martyrs</hi>) it was, ſo, unto <hi>you</hi> it <hi>is,</hi>
                        <note n="(r)" place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29.</note> 
                        <hi>given</hi> to <hi>beleeve;</hi> Is it a <hi>marvel</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>You,</hi> if, as it likewiſe <hi>was</hi> unto <hi>them,</hi> ſo it <hi>is</hi> unto <hi>You, given</hi> to <hi>ſuffer?</hi> It is your <hi>comfort,</hi> that ye are <hi>Sons</hi> and not <hi>Bastards?</hi> And would ye be <hi>treated</hi> like <hi>Baſtards,</hi> and not like Sons? If ye would,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Since (at this inſtant) your <hi>chastiſement</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, not <hi>joyous,</hi> but <hi>greivous;</hi> Bleſſe ye your God, for that <hi>your</hi> afflictions <hi>equall</hi> not <hi>Abrahams.</hi> They<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10.</note> ſhall <hi>mourn</hi> as for an <hi>onely Son,</hi> To <hi>part</hi> with a <hi>child,</hi> and <hi>He</hi> a <hi>child</hi> growing <hi>tall,</hi> as well in <hi>expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation,</hi> as in <hi>stature:</hi> One who might hereafter have bin the <hi>staff</hi> of our <hi>old age,</hi> and was, for the preſent, the <hi>Deſire</hi> of our <hi>eyes:</hi> to <hi>loſe</hi> the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of a <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Heir,</hi> then when that <hi>onely Son</hi> began to <hi>rejoyce</hi> onely <hi>in the Lord;</hi> this is (indeed) no <hi>ordinarie</hi> triall: Yet (Give God the Glorie) as <hi>ſmart</hi> as our <hi>preſent chastiſement</hi> is, it is not ſo <hi>greivous</hi> as the <hi>temptation</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> was. Who have bin unto
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:95939:28"/> God the <hi>truer friends,</hi> We or the <hi>Patriarch?</hi> Whoſe <hi>temptations</hi> have bin the <hi>greater,</hi> the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> or <hi>Ours?</hi> Weigh we, <hi>in the ſame ballance,</hi> the <hi>burden,</hi> the <hi>number,</hi> the <hi>ſharpeneſse,</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>trialls</hi> with <hi>our own;</hi> we ſhall then <hi>feele</hi> our <hi>own</hi> to be, as the <hi>Apostle</hi> juſtly <hi>esteemeth</hi> them, <hi>light afflictions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Since he was a <hi>Friend of God</hi> who was thus <hi>tempted,</hi> Bleſſe thou thy God ſo often as he <hi>bestow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> upon thee the <hi>favour</hi> of a <hi>correction:</hi> They who were <hi>fortie</hi> yeares <hi>humbled</hi> in the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> were not <hi>Moabites,</hi> or <hi>Amonites,</hi> but the <hi>choſen people</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> and, when upon <hi>their back</hi> the <hi>plowers plowed</hi> long <hi>furrows,</hi> it was that out of that <hi>heart</hi> which was once <hi>fallow ground,</hi> they might <hi>bring forth</hi> a <hi>plentiful harvect.</hi> It is not the <hi>chaff,</hi> but the <hi>wheate,</hi> which men <hi>take paines</hi> to <hi>winnow,</hi> and the <hi>better</hi> the <hi>wheat,</hi> the more <hi>throughly</hi> it is <hi>ſifted.</hi> We give no ſuch <hi>diligence</hi> to <hi>melt lead</hi> or <hi>tinn,</hi> as is uſed in <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineing,</hi> either <hi>Silver</hi> or <hi>Gold;</hi> and, of <hi>Gold</hi> the <hi>lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> the <hi>Wedge</hi> or <hi>ingott,</hi> the more <hi>fierie</hi> the <hi>trial.</hi> It is the <hi>Vine branch</hi> that beareth <hi>Fruite,</hi> which the <hi>Husband-man pruneth;</hi> and, the <hi>choicer</hi> the <hi>grape,</hi> the more <hi>industrious</hi> is the <hi>Hus-bandman.</hi> When the Lord maketh up his <hi>jewells,</hi> he firſt <hi>fileth,</hi> and then <hi>poliſheth,</hi> them; and, the <hi>dearer</hi> his <hi>children</hi> are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Him,</hi> the <hi>stricter</hi> is their <hi>education:</hi> Caſt <hi>Daniel</hi> into a <hi>furnace</hi> of <hi>fire,</hi> and you make him the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion</hi> of an <hi>Angel;</hi> While God giveth unto you a <hi>priviledge</hi> to <hi>endure temptations,</hi> he giveth unto you a <hi>fellow-ſhip</hi> in the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi> But then</p>
                     <p n="4">4. See that ye <hi>loſe</hi> not the <hi>benefit</hi> of your <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:95939:28"/> (If thou wilt <hi>thank</hi> thy <hi>God</hi> for giving thee <hi>warning:</hi>) while the <hi>warning</hi> is <hi>hott,</hi> let not the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of <hi>grace</hi> coole. Thy <hi>bitter herbes</hi> are <hi>phyſical,</hi> uſe them afore they be <hi>withered:</hi> God <hi>intendeth</hi> our <hi>spiritual health,</hi> as ever we would receive <hi>no hurt</hi> by this <hi>phyſick,</hi> let our <hi>endeavours</hi> ſecond His <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> There are <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>Degrees,</hi> yea and <hi>croſses</hi> of <hi>Degrees</hi> too; if we be not wanting unto <hi>our ſelves,</hi> we may by theſe, as upon the <hi>rounds</hi> of <hi>Jacobs</hi> lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>climbe</hi> the <hi>Heavens:</hi> It was, by a <hi>whirl-wind,</hi> that <hi>Elijah</hi> was <hi>taken up.</hi> If thou art <hi>ſmitten</hi> to the <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>astoniſhed,</hi> as He (<hi>Act.</hi> IX.) was; <hi>tremble</hi> as He did, and <hi>with Him,</hi> ſay, Lord, What <hi>wilt</hi> thou <hi>have mee to do?</hi> That our <hi>Sorrow</hi> may be <hi>turned</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Joy,</hi> let the <hi>temptation</hi> wherein we are <hi>fallen</hi> have its <hi>perfect work.</hi> God <hi>tried</hi> graceleſſe <hi>Saul,</hi> and God <hi>tempted</hi> Faithfull <hi>Abraham;</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> was <hi>tried, Saul</hi> ſpared <hi>Agag:</hi> but when <hi>Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BE <hi>afraid</hi> therefore ye <hi>ſinners</hi> who <hi>trample</hi> under <hi>foote</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and be ye <hi>horribly</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid ye <hi>Atheists</hi> who <hi>crucifie</hi> unto <hi>your ſelves</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Glorie.</hi> I<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>line.</hi> 24.</note> was ſaying, If <hi>Faithfull Abraham</hi> was <hi>tempted</hi> and <hi>afflicted,</hi> perſons that are <hi>ungodly</hi> could not in this life <hi>expect</hi> to continue <hi>un-afflicted</hi> long: Let mee now, add.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. If the <hi>iniquitie</hi> of your <hi>heeles</hi> do not <hi>overtake</hi> you, and <hi>compaſse</hi> you about before ye <hi>Die;</hi> If there be no <hi>Death</hi> in your <hi>hands;</hi> If you come not into
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:95939:29"/> 
                        <hi>troubles</hi> like <hi>other men;</hi> it is, that your <hi>proſperitie</hi> may <hi>deſtroy</hi> you: If the <hi>patience</hi> of the <hi>all-ſeeing</hi> God ſuffer you to <hi>fill up</hi> the <hi>meaſure</hi> of your <hi>offences,</hi> it is, that ye may not be <hi>able</hi> to <hi>abide</hi> the <hi>day</hi> of his <hi>coming.</hi> If He that <hi>cometh</hi> to <hi>judg terribly</hi> the earth, letteth you <hi>alone</hi> to <hi>feede</hi> the <hi>evil imaginations</hi> of your <hi>heart</hi> in <hi>quiet;</hi> it is, that (like the <hi>Deere</hi> in your <hi>Parks</hi> of <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and like the <hi>Oxon</hi> in your <hi>pasture-ground</hi>) ye may be <hi>fatted</hi> againſt the day of <hi>ſlaughter. One</hi> eſpeciall <hi>reaſon</hi> why <hi>whole burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings were</hi> at the firſt <hi>instituted,</hi> was, to ſignifie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, that<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.29.</note> 
                        <hi>our God is a conſuming fire.</hi> viz. <hi>everie man</hi> that is not <hi>ſeaſoned</hi> with the <hi>Salt</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> ſhall <note n="(u)" place="margin">
                           <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.49.</note> be <hi>ſalted</hi> with the <hi>fire</hi> of <hi>Tophet.</hi> Such as are <hi>ſanctified</hi> by the <hi>fire</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> ſhall (like <hi>Iſaac</hi>) be unto God<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16.</note> an <hi>acceptable burnt offering;</hi> Such as do not by faith <hi>purifie</hi> their <hi>heart</hi> and their <hi>whole</hi> man, from <hi>dead works,</hi> to <hi>ſerve</hi> the <hi>living</hi> God, ſhall be not like <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but like that Ram which (in the <hi>stead</hi> of <hi>Iſaac) Abraham</hi> offered up, they ſhall be<note n="(y)" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal</hi> 37.20.</note> as the <hi>fatt</hi> of <hi>Lambs,</hi> they ſhall everlaſtingly <hi>conſume;</hi> into <hi>ſmoke</hi> ſhall they <hi>conſume</hi> away <hi>for ever</hi> Nevertheleſſe,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. How <hi>desperately wicked</hi> ſoever thou haſt bin in <hi>times past,</hi> for the <hi>time to come</hi> here is <hi>open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> unto thee a <hi>door</hi> of <hi>hope:</hi> for 1. He who ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>accepted</hi> the <hi>Ram, testifieth</hi> even <hi>unto thee</hi> that His <hi>Delight</hi> is, not in <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> but in <hi>mercies</hi> 2. When this <hi>only ſon</hi> was <hi>offered</hi> upon the <hi>Altar,</hi> he was then a type of that <hi>ſon</hi> of <hi>God</hi> who is made a <hi>Propitiation</hi> for thy <hi>Sins:</hi> 3. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:95939:29"/> 
                        <hi>Iſaac</hi> was <hi>bound,</hi> His God <hi>releaſed</hi> him; and, although thou art <hi>tyed</hi> and <hi>bound</hi> in the <hi>cords</hi> of thy <hi>Sins,</hi> the <hi>ſame God</hi> would <hi>releaſe</hi> even thee. 4. After <hi>Iſaac</hi> was <hi>releaſed,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> bleſſed <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ac;</hi> wouldeſt thou <hi>riſe</hi> and <hi>walk,</hi> God hath for thee, ſtore of <hi>bleſſings;</hi> O <hi>taste</hi> and <hi>ſee</hi> that the LORD is good. But 5. What ſort of <hi>Darling</hi> is this <hi>Dalilah</hi> which thou <hi>preferrest</hi> before the <hi>poſseſſiour</hi> of <hi>heaven</hi> and of <hi>earth? Anſw.</hi> A <hi>ſeeming,</hi> and but a <hi>ſeeming,</hi> pleaſure of <hi>Sin;</hi> In this age, there is in ſome Sins no <hi>ſort</hi> of <hi>Delight,</hi> except they be <hi>infamous</hi> as well as <hi>Wicked:</hi> There is no <hi>pleaſure</hi> in <hi>diceing,</hi> except the <hi>Patrimonie</hi> be <hi>sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> as well as the <hi>Guiney: Apples</hi> of <hi>Sodom</hi> are no <hi>raritie</hi> at moſt <hi>Banquets:</hi> The <hi>apparel</hi> of ſome men were not in <hi>faſhion,</hi> were it not of more <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue</hi> then a <hi>years révenue</hi> will <hi>pay for:</hi> Neither are they <hi>welcome</hi> at a <hi>feaſt,</hi> except they be ſo <hi>drunk</hi> that they need a <hi>withdrawing room.</hi> The <hi>cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs</hi> of ſome <hi>Miſers</hi> is ſo <hi>idolatrous,</hi> that they ſet their <hi>hearts</hi> more upon their <hi>riches,</hi> then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>that God</hi> which <hi>giveth</hi> them a <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>get wealth:</hi> and ſuch is the <hi>Luxurie</hi> of others, as if <hi>riches</hi> could not make unto themſelves <hi>wings,</hi> were there no <hi>Feathers</hi> to be <hi>found in</hi> their <hi>caps.</hi> Tell me now, in <hi>cool blood:</hi> Head-aking <hi>drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> unclean <hi>lusts, (Luſts</hi> which make thy <hi>bones</hi> rotten, as well as thy <hi>communication;</hi>) unthriftie <hi>riots,</hi> weariſom <hi>idleneſs,</hi> wide-mouthed <hi>Oathes,</hi> ungodly <hi>jeſtings,</hi> unbleſſed <hi>vanities,</hi> (Vanities <hi>linked together</hi> by that <hi>Prince of Darkneſs</hi> who
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:95939:30"/> with them <hi>chaineth</hi> thee unto his <hi>bottomleſs</hi> Pitt:) Are theſe the <hi>Iſaacs</hi> which thou art <hi>fond</hi> of? Wouldeſt thou rather eternally Sacrifice thy ſelf a <hi>burnt offering</hi> in <hi>hell torments,</hi> then <hi>Sacrificce</hi> theſe <hi>needleſs</hi> evils? For ſhame <hi>mortifie</hi> thou thoſe <hi>follies</hi> which, if thou <hi>dieſt not unto them,</hi> will be unto thee <hi>death eternal.</hi> Wouldeſt thou <hi>break off</hi> that <hi>yoke,</hi> cleave that <hi>wood,</hi> which hath hitherto prepared <hi>fewel</hi> for <hi>hell fire,</hi> wouldeſt thou make Jeſus Chriſt thine <hi>altar,</hi> and upon that altar ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice thine <hi>Iſaac,</hi> even thy <hi>whole man;</hi> wouldeſt thou <hi>Crucifie</hi> thy <hi>lusts,</hi> ſtudie <hi>ſelf denial,</hi> and place thine <hi>endeavours</hi> upon exerciſing <hi>thy ſelf</hi> unto <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> thy <hi>Delights</hi> upon the <hi>pleaſantneſs</hi> of <hi>new obedience,</hi> and thine <hi>affections</hi> upon things <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and heavenly;</hi> He that can <hi>abundantly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and is <hi>mightie to ſave,</hi> would ſay unto <hi>thy ſoul,</hi> as he ſaid unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> now Know I that <hi>thou</hi> feareſt <hi>God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Whereas it is feared that <hi>this people</hi> of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> hath a <hi>revolting</hi> and a <hi>rebellious heart,</hi> our <hi>backslidings</hi> will <hi>quickly ceaſe,</hi> if we take out that <hi>pattern</hi> which is here given unto us by this <hi>Father of many nations.</hi> Bleſſed be <hi>our God,</hi> we have a <hi>gracious King;</hi> we have <hi>excellent Lawes;</hi> we have <hi>Judges</hi> which do, at every <hi>Aſſize,</hi> give a <hi>charge</hi> that theſe <hi>Laws</hi> be duly <hi>executed;</hi> unto theſe <hi>Judges,</hi> we have <hi>ſubordinate Magistrates;</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate unto theſe, <hi>Magistrates,</hi> we have <hi>ſworn Officers;</hi> ſubordinate unto theſe, <hi>Houſe Keepers;</hi>
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:95939:30"/> and unto theſe, their <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants.</hi> It was, when <hi>Eli</hi> hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap> his <hi>Sons</hi> more then God, that <hi>matters</hi> went <hi>amiſs</hi> with <hi>Him</hi> and His <hi>people:</hi> but, when <hi>Phinehas</hi> ſtood up and <hi>executed Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> then was the <hi>Plague stayed.</hi> If <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Masters</hi> offer up their <hi>Iſaacs,</hi> their <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> to be duly <hi>Catechiſed;</hi> ſo duly <hi>Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> that the <hi>fear of the Lord</hi> is unto them <hi>their treaſure;</hi> this will lay ſo <hi>good</hi> a <hi>foundation</hi> of a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperous government,</hi> that <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> will be the <hi>Stabilitie of our times. Parents</hi> and <hi>Masters</hi> will <hi>constrain</hi> their <hi>Familes</hi> to <hi>ſubmit unto</hi> their own <hi>happineſs,</hi> that is, to learn <hi>Catechiſmes,</hi> to <hi>frequent</hi> the <hi>publick worſhip</hi> of the <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Christ,</hi> and to <hi>ſanctifie</hi> God in <hi>their hearts;</hi> when, at every <hi>Seſſion</hi> and <hi>Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſworn <hi>officers</hi> offer up their <hi>Iſaac,</hi> as well as their <hi>preſentments; that is,</hi> when they ſo <hi>denie themſelves</hi> that they preſent <hi>all ſuch</hi> as will not <hi>denie ungodlineſs;</hi> and when they ſuffer not <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations</hi> to <hi>crumble</hi> into <hi>Meetings,</hi> or rather, into no <hi>Meetings,</hi> And this <hi>Sworn Officers</hi> will be <hi>glad to do,</hi> when they are <hi>made</hi> to <hi>fear an Oath.</hi> And, an <hi>Oath</hi> they will <hi>fear,</hi> when at, <hi>Seſſions</hi> and at <hi>Viſitations,</hi> our Rulers <hi>rule with diligence,</hi> and <hi>offer up</hi> their <hi>Iſaacs.</hi> And this <hi>they</hi> will do, when (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Religion</hi> their <hi>buſineſs</hi>) they <hi>prefer</hi> the <hi>favour of God,</hi> before the <hi>favour of man.</hi> Ye therefore, <hi>beloved,</hi> ſeeing ye know <hi>theſe things</hi> before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware leſt any of you <hi>being led away</hi> with the <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> of the <hi>wicked,</hi> fall from your own <hi>Stedfast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:95939:31"/> Who knoweth whether he is not born <hi>in this Kingdom</hi> for <hi>ſuch a time</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>? God will do ſo to him <hi>and more alſo,</hi> who <hi>when he is</hi> there unto <hi>called,</hi> doth not <hi>offer up</hi> his <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Let the <hi>ſelf denials</hi> of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhame every one among us into a <hi>greater Watchfulneſs</hi> &amp;c. He, at the (b) firſt <hi>intimation,</hi> aroſe (c) <hi>early,</hi> went on <hi>diligently,</hi> perſevered (d) <hi>constantly</hi> to <hi>obſerve,</hi> againſt his <hi>own will,</hi> the <hi>will of</hi> his <hi>God;</hi> chuſing rather to be an <hi>unnatural parent,</hi> then an <hi>unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant:</hi> Whereas ſome of us have delaied, <hi>from year to year,</hi> before we would <hi>yeild</hi> to <hi>take up our</hi> daily <hi>croſs: precept</hi> upon <hi>precept, line</hi> upon <hi>line</hi> we have <hi>received,</hi> but what <hi>anſwer</hi> have we <hi>returned</hi> unto him that hath <hi>written</hi> unto us the <hi>honourable things</hi> of His <hi>law, Statutes,</hi> which if a man <hi>would do,</hi> he might <hi>even</hi> live <hi>in them?</hi> Thou who <hi>conformeſt thy ſelf</hi> unto the <hi>licentiouſneſs</hi> of an <hi>evil world,</hi> Did this <hi>Patriarch,</hi> at one <hi>private Item,</hi> ſurrender his <hi>only Son,</hi> and will not all the <hi>publick Commandements</hi> which thy God hath <hi>in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-kindneſ,</hi> laid upon thee, <hi>prevail</hi> with thy <hi>lips,</hi> to <hi>bite in</hi> a <hi>vain oath,</hi> with thine <hi>appetite,</hi> to <hi>forbeare</hi> an <hi>un healthy</hi> ſin, with thy <hi>memorie</hi> to <hi>treaſure up</hi> Heavenly <hi>Knowledge,</hi> or, with thine <hi>understanding,</hi> to <hi>perform Duties profitable, comely</hi> and of <hi>good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</hi> The more <hi>eaſie</hi> that <hi>yoke</hi> is which Chriſt <hi>laieth</hi> upon us, the more <hi>careful ſhould</hi> we <hi>be</hi> to follow the <hi>example</hi> of this <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Iſaac;</hi> otherwiſe, the <hi>burnt offering</hi> which he <hi>with-held</hi> not, will, <hi>at the last day,</hi>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:95939:31"/> be <hi>offered</hi> in <hi>judgment</hi> againſt us. Be not <hi>deceived,</hi> God is not <hi>mocked:</hi> as a man <hi>ſacrificeth,</hi> ſo is he <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4 Since <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> learne thou of him to hold <hi>every bleſſing</hi> which thou recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt from God, with a <hi>minde prepared</hi> to <hi>reſigne</hi> it to God. <hi>Jehovah,</hi> he is the <hi>Lord poſſeſſour</hi> as of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> ſo of <hi>Earth;</hi> and whatſoever <hi>mercie</hi> thou <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveſt</hi> from him, that thou <hi>receivest</hi> but <hi>during his will and pleaſure:</hi> What thou <hi>obtaineſt</hi> by <hi>praier</hi> is but <hi>borrowed,</hi> and to <hi>grudge</hi> when thou art to pay what was but <hi>borrowed,</hi> is <hi>flatt diſhoneſtie:</hi> What thou <hi>enjoyeſt from God</hi> is neither <hi>deſerved,</hi> nor <hi>purchaſed,</hi> but by the <hi>providence,</hi> and <hi>goodneſs,</hi> and <hi>loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of thy <hi>liberal Master,</hi> it is <hi>intruſted</hi> with thee for thy <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>conveniences,</hi> but for His <hi>uſes, ſervice,</hi> and <hi>honour;</hi> It is favour enough for thee, that God hath <hi>owned</hi> and <hi>entertained</hi> thee as His <hi>steward,</hi> Wherefore (when at any time thy God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth from thee ſome <hi>child,</hi> or ſome other <hi>comfort</hi>) of <hi>his own</hi> thou <hi>giveſt</hi> him, <hi>murmure</hi> not, <hi>repine</hi> not, be not, in any wiſe, be not thou <hi>diſcontented</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe thou a <hi>Good is the word of the Lord;</hi> Aſſent thou, <hi>the will of</hi> the Lord <hi>be done;</hi> Say thou, <hi>He is</hi> the Lord, <hi>whatſoever</hi> he <hi>pleaſeth, that let</hi> Him <hi>doe;</hi> As well when he <hi>taketh,</hi> as when he <hi>giveth,</hi> bleſſe thou <hi>the Name of the Lord.</hi> It is very <hi>obſervable</hi> that (twenty ſix yeares ſince) when there was but <hi>one night</hi> between <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>deſtruction,</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> then uſed <hi>earneſt prayers</hi> and <hi>arguments</hi> to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:95939:32"/> ſave, if it were <hi>poſſible,</hi> that <hi>wicked Citie</hi> from <hi>peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing:</hi> for the <hi>Men of Sodom</hi> he <hi>mediated</hi> ſeven times <hi>in a breath,</hi> for his <hi>blameleſse</hi> and <hi>dearest</hi> Son, he <hi>intercedeth</hi> not: <hi>Qu:</hi> Why this? <hi>Anſw:</hi> Holy <hi>Abraham</hi> loved one righteous <hi>Iſaac</hi> more then all the <hi>ſinners</hi> of <hi>Sodom,</hi> but (ſo it was) God had revealed concerning <hi>Sodom</hi> onely a <hi>conditional pleaſure,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing "<hi>I will</hi> go <hi>down and ſee;</hi> Concerning <hi>Iſaac</hi> he had <hi>revealed</hi> his <hi>abſolute pleaſure,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Take now:</hi> Wherefore ſo <hi>abſolute</hi> is the <hi>Patriarch</hi> his <hi>reſignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that notwithſtanding his God had <hi>yeelded</hi> unto him <hi>ſeven times together</hi> in all that he had ſpoken in the <hi>behalf</hi> of <hi>Sodom;</hi> he doth not at all <hi>open his lips</hi> unto God in <hi>behalf</hi> of his <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Go thou, and do likewiſe: When God ſaith <hi>Offer up,</hi> with-hold not <hi>thou.</hi> Being called unto <hi>ſelf-denials,</hi> Let <hi>Duty</hi> teach thee not to <hi>argue,</hi> but to <hi>ſubmitt;</hi> not to <hi>diſpute</hi> but to <hi>obey;</hi> not to <hi>request,</hi> but to <hi>reſigne.</hi> Let thy <hi>meek,</hi> thine <hi>humble,</hi> thy <hi>modest,</hi> thought be "I am <hi>dumb;</hi> I <hi>open not</hi> my <hi>mouth,</hi> becauſe thou doeſt it. Nay</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Since <hi>thou owest</hi> not onely <hi>whatſoever is</hi> in thy <hi>custodie</hi> but even <hi>thy ſelfe</hi> alſo unto Him that is <hi>Lord of all, Araunah</hi> like, <hi>meete thou</hi> thy King <hi>in</hi> His <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.</hi> Make <hi>friends</hi> of unrighteous <hi>Mammon:</hi> What thou mayeſt not <hi>detaine,</hi> that <hi>give,</hi> and give <hi>cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> unto Him who <hi>loveth</hi> a chearefull <hi>Giver</hi> What thy God calleth for, that <hi>preſent, dedicate</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate,</hi> firſt <hi>love</hi> thy <hi>Relations</hi> as <hi>dearly</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> loved <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and then eſteem <hi>Father, Mother, Wife, Children,</hi> and (with them) whatſoever elſe is <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious,</hi>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:95939:32"/> eſteem all of them together, too <hi>ſmall,</hi> too <hi>mean,</hi> a <hi>preſent,</hi> to <hi>testifie</hi> the <hi>readineſse</hi> of thy <hi>devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or the <hi>ſinceritie</hi> of thy <hi>gratitude,</hi> unto the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Giver</hi> of thy Lord Jeſus Chriſt: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing ſo many as he <hi>loveth,</hi> them he <hi>chastneth,</hi> and ſo many as he <hi>chastneth</hi> them he <hi>chastneth</hi> for the <hi>spiritual</hi> and <hi>eternal</hi> good of <hi>themſelves,</hi> or of <hi>others,</hi> or of <hi>both:</hi> whether</p>
                     <p n="1">1. For the <hi>benefit</hi> of <hi>others.</hi> Accompt upon it that wherein the <hi>God of all comfort</hi> doth <hi>comfort</hi> us in all our <hi>tribulation,</hi> therein he <hi>prepareth</hi> and <hi>bespea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth</hi> us to <hi>comfort</hi> them who are in any <hi>trouble</hi> by the <hi>comfort</hi> wherewith we <hi>ourſelves</hi> are <hi>comforted</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Are the <hi>conſolations</hi> of <hi>God</hi> ſmall <hi>with thee?</hi> (I hope not) Or</p>
                     <p n="2">2. By <hi>casting down</hi> thine <hi>old</hi> and <hi>outward man,</hi> thy God <hi>preventeth</hi> thy <hi>new,</hi> thine <hi>inward, man</hi> from <hi>falling. Jeſurum,</hi> when he waxed <hi>fatt, Kic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked;</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> when he was <hi>full, denied</hi> God: So is it with thee, and with other <hi>Saints:</hi> Alas, the more holy mens <hi>lives</hi> are, the more <hi>advantage Satan ſeeketh</hi> to <hi>gett</hi> over them; that <hi>old Serpent</hi> well knowing, (by his <hi>own</hi> woful <hi>experience,</hi>) that there is no <hi>pride</hi> like unto <hi>Spiritual pride:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that even the <hi>Fall</hi> of his <hi>children</hi> may <hi>bruiſe</hi> this Serpents <hi>head,</hi> when the <hi>right hand</hi> of God <hi>exalteth</hi> them, moſt uſually his <hi>left hand</hi> doth <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> them; It is indeed unto their <hi>humiliation</hi> (but it is, ſo unto their <hi>humiliation,</hi> that it <hi>conduceth</hi> unto their <hi>honour</hi>) that God doth ſo often place them in the <hi>forlorn hope:</hi> When no man upon earth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:95939:33"/> was ſo <hi>upright</hi> as <hi>Job,</hi> then was the <hi>roaring Lion</hi> let <hi>loſe againſt him;</hi> After <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had pleaded <hi>ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> God gave him a <hi>taste</hi> of his <hi>unprosperous vain gloriouſneſs; David</hi> was <hi>confeſſedly</hi> a <hi>man</hi> after <hi>Gods</hi> own <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>as confeſſedly Adulterie, Murder,</hi> and <hi>Pride</hi> it ſelf, brought him very Low. <hi>Jacob</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed when he <hi>wrastled</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> but God ſent him <hi>halting</hi> away: Who more <hi>ſtout hearted</hi> then <hi>Peter,</hi> and who more <hi>cowheartedly</hi> denied his <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus? Satan</hi> had not bin <hi>permitted</hi> to <hi>buffet Paul,</hi> had not <hi>Paul</hi> bin <hi>exalted</hi> by <hi>abundant Revelations. Moſes</hi> was a <hi>meek man,</hi> but he ſpake ſo <hi>unadviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with</hi> his <hi>lips,</hi> that there was for him no <hi>Entrance</hi> into <hi>Canaan: Abraham</hi> ſo <hi>excelled</hi> in <hi>Faith</hi> that he was <hi>exemplarily</hi> and <hi>eminently</hi> the <hi>Father of the Faithful,</hi> but where was the <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Abraham,</hi> when (more then once) he <hi>diſſembled</hi> that <hi>Sarah</hi> was only his <hi>Sister?</hi> And as (that he who thinketh he ſtandeth may take heed leſt he fall) the <hi>wiſest</hi> of <hi>men</hi> was made a <hi>mere fool</hi> by the <hi>Vilest</hi> of <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> ſo (that we may not be <hi>ignorant</hi> of the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi>) Chriſt himſelf when he was firſt <hi>baptized,</hi> next <hi>endued</hi> with the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and then <hi>declared,</hi> mightily declared, to be the <hi>Son of God,</hi> was <hi>afterwards</hi> led into the <hi>Wilderneſs;</hi> and, in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> forty daies together, <hi>tempted</hi> of the <hi>Devil.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. To <hi>rouſe</hi> a <hi>Soul</hi> from <hi>drowſineſs,</hi> to <hi>purſue</hi> ſome <hi>unrepented Crime,</hi> to <hi>diſlodge</hi> ſome <hi>boſom Sin,</hi> &amp;c. It was when <hi>Saul</hi> failed of his <hi>expectation,</hi> that <hi>Jonathan</hi> was <hi>questioned</hi> for <hi>eating honey:</hi> and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:95939:33"/> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was <hi>repelled,</hi> then was the <hi>Sacriledge</hi> of <hi>Acham</hi> diſcoved. Before he was <hi>troubled, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> himſelf <hi>went wrong;</hi> and, until he was <hi>cast</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>troubled Sea, Jonah</hi> fled from the <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>Lord.</hi> Many times there is in our <hi>calamities</hi> a <hi>Spirit of diſcerning;</hi> while, like that <hi>Angel</hi> which met <hi>Baalam,</hi> they give us to underſtand our <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent miſadventures. Search me,</hi> O Lord, <hi>and know</hi> my heart, <hi>trie me and know</hi> my thoughts, <hi>See if there be</hi> in me <hi>any way of pain:</hi> A <hi>daily praier</hi> (this) and this <hi>praier</hi> almoſt <hi>every day,</hi> before we call <hi>God anſwereth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. To <hi>ſatisfie</hi> our ſelves, or others, of the <hi>truth,</hi> or <hi>groweth</hi> of our <hi>Graces;</hi> it is the <hi>furnace</hi> that as well <hi>approveth</hi> as <hi>trieth Silver;</hi> The <hi>ſame trial</hi> which <hi>inviteth worldlings</hi> to <hi>esteem Preachers</hi> no better then <hi>earthen Pitchers;</hi> the <hi>ſelf ſame trial</hi> occaſioneth <hi>every one that appeareth before God,</hi> to <hi>look upon</hi> thoſe <hi>Preachers,</hi> as upon the <hi>precious Sons</hi> of <hi>Zion,</hi> and to <hi>value</hi> thoſe <hi>precious Sons</hi> of <hi>Zion</hi> comparable unto <hi>fine gold:</hi> the which the more it is tried, the better it is <hi>refined;</hi> and the more it is <hi>refined,</hi> the <hi>brighter</hi> it <hi>ſhineth:</hi> The <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> which all theſe holy <hi>Martyrs</hi> in this whole <hi>context endured,</hi> were, not only the <hi>trials,</hi> but the <hi>vindications;</hi> not only the <hi>vindications,</hi> but the <hi>approbations;</hi> not only the <hi>approbations,</hi> but the <hi>publications,</hi> and <hi>recommendations</hi> of their <hi>Faith:</hi> Such was their <hi>Faith,</hi> that, to their <hi>praiſe</hi> be it <hi>spoken,</hi> their <hi>names</hi> are <hi>Regiſtred</hi> by the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> himſelf. That <hi>poor widow</hi> was made <hi>rich</hi> by the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:95939:34"/> 
                        <hi>applauſes</hi> of <hi>Christ Jeſus,</hi> when he <hi>vouchſafed</hi> to <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute</hi> a <hi>greater munificence</hi> unto her <hi>ſmall mite,</hi> then unto the largeſt gifts that were caſt unto the <hi>Treaſurie.</hi> The like was the <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> of that <hi>true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Mary,</hi> unto whom the ſame <hi>bleſsed Jeſus</hi> gave this <hi>felicitie,</hi> that where ſoever His Holy <hi>Gospel</hi> ſhall be <hi>preached,</hi> there her Name ſhall be as <hi>ointment pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth:</hi> In every deed neither the <hi>deare-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of that <hi>penitent,</hi> nor the <hi>plain dealing</hi> of <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> nor the <hi>meekeneſse</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Elijah,</hi> had ever bin one half ſo <hi>famous</hi> as they now are, had not <hi>malicious tongues</hi> given occaſion to have the <hi>excellencie</hi> of their <hi>graces</hi> brought to the <hi>test.</hi> Said that envious <hi>Eliab</hi> unto his brother <hi>David,</hi> I know the <hi>pride</hi> and the <hi>naughtineſse</hi> of thy <hi>heart;</hi> but where was <hi>David</hi> his <hi>pride,</hi> when he refuſed the <hi>costly armour</hi> of <hi>King Saul,</hi> and <hi>contented himſelf,</hi> with a <hi>ſling</hi> and a <hi>stone?</hi> Or, where was the <hi>naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of his <hi>heart,</hi> when in <hi>love</hi> toward his <hi>nation,</hi> and in <hi>Zeal</hi> toward his <hi>God,</hi> he <hi>staked</hi> his <hi>own life</hi> againſt the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>Goliah?</hi> Again, as <hi>trials</hi> are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times <hi>inflicted</hi> to ſhew what ſome <hi>choſen Saints</hi> can <hi>bear,</hi> ſo</p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>Afflictions abide</hi> moſt of <hi>us,</hi> becauſe moſt of us, remain hitherto <hi>un-able</hi> to <hi>bear</hi> an <hi>un-afflicted</hi> life; Except we <hi>hear</hi> the <hi>rod,</hi> &amp; Him who hath <hi>appointed</hi> it, many of us will not be <hi>ruled:</hi> Even ſo much that the <hi>Heir,</hi> ſo long as he is a <hi>child,</hi> is under <hi>Tutors</hi> and <hi>Governors.</hi> Let <hi>Abſolom</hi> return unto his <hi>private houſe,</hi> for at <hi>Court</hi> he will <hi>ruin himſelf,</hi> and that, <hi>without remedie.</hi> Should we
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:95939:34"/> 
                        <hi>Britains</hi> forget what we have <hi>ſeen</hi> and <hi>felt</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> they at <hi>Munster</hi> will tell us that a <hi>ſword</hi> is un-ſafe in <hi>Anabaptists</hi> hands. Some in this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> who now <hi>receive Alms,</hi> would <hi>attempt inſolent practices,</hi> were they <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Mannor.</hi> A <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> is ſo <hi>apt</hi> to be <hi>puffed</hi> up with <hi>pride,</hi> that he is no <hi>fit perſon</hi> to be a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> neither is <hi>honour</hi> ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a <hi>fool.</hi> Even the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> before he could (with a <hi>due moderation,</hi> and with a <hi>requiſite ſobrietie</hi>) be <hi>prepared</hi> to <hi>inherit</hi> the <hi>promiſed rest,</hi> was <hi>forty years</hi> long <hi>humbled</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs.</hi> But I hope <hi>better things</hi> of you <hi>(my brethren:)</hi> I truſt that the <hi>God of</hi> all <hi>grace,</hi> after ye have ſuffered <hi>a little while,</hi> will make you <hi>meet</hi> to be <hi>partakers</hi> of the <hi>inheritance</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> in light.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Many times (whileſt we ſeem <hi>distreſsed</hi>) Out of our <hi>diſtreſses</hi> (as out of the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> of <hi>Lazarous</hi>) God is <hi>fetching</hi> about ſome <hi>honour</hi> unto Himſelf: In which caſe <hi>What</hi> he <hi>doth,</hi> that <hi>thou knowest not</hi> now, <hi>but</hi> hereafter <hi>thou</hi> ſhalt <hi>know.</hi> Verily thoſe <hi>waters</hi> wherewith <hi>Chriſt</hi> waſheth the <hi>unclean feet</hi> of our vile <hi>affections,</hi> are (like water at <hi>Infant-baptiſm</hi>) no leſs <hi>future,</hi> then <hi>preſent, healings.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> made <hi>Naaman</hi> leprous that he might <hi>waſh</hi> in Jordan, and that (by <hi>waſhing</hi> in <hi>Jordan</hi>) he might <hi>cleanſe,</hi> rather his <hi>Soul,</hi> then his <hi>body.</hi> Into that <hi>river</hi> the <hi>axe head</hi> fell, but, loe, <hi>iron</hi> ſhall <hi>ſwimm.</hi> If the <hi>poor beggar</hi> was <hi>born blind,</hi> it was that the <hi>Son</hi> of a <hi>God</hi> might work a <hi>miracle</hi> upon his <hi>eyes. Jonah</hi> was not <hi>cast away,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 9.3.</note> when into the Sea he was caſt; for him the <hi>Lord provided</hi> a <hi>Whale,</hi>
                        <pb n="62" facs="tcp:95939:35"/> and in (the <hi>Whale</hi>) a <hi>Noahs</hi> ark<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren thought <hi>evil</hi> againſt him, but <hi>God</hi> meant it for <hi>good:</hi> He was a <hi>lost man,</hi> that he might <hi>ſave</hi> much peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>alive;</hi> Into <hi>Egypt</hi> he was <hi>ſold,</hi> that of <hi>Egypt</hi> he might <hi>dispoſe.</hi> Let his <hi>mother</hi> hide <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>flags,</hi> and the <hi>Kings daughter</hi> ſhall give him a <hi>Princely education:</hi> Give him a <hi>Princely educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> he will be <hi>learned</hi> in all the <hi>learning</hi> of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians;</hi> ſo <hi>learned,</hi> that he will <hi>overmatch Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> and ſhall (with a high hand) bring Gods <hi>firſt born</hi> out of <hi>bondage.</hi> The <hi>captivitie</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> how did it <hi>conduce</hi> both unto his own <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement,</hi> and unto the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To conclude this point: With his onely ſon the <hi>father</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> muſt part; but What <hi>ſhall be</hi> ſeen <hi>in the</hi> mount <hi>of the</hi> Lord, <hi>Who</hi> can <hi>tell?</hi> Who knoweth whether there may not out of the <hi>Dust</hi> of this <hi>Grave</hi> ariſe, as well <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>rejoycing,</hi> as <hi>cauſes</hi> of <hi>ſorrow;</hi> as well the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>grace,</hi> as <hi>drie bones?</hi> With God it is not <hi>impoſſible,</hi> but that (while I <hi>preach</hi> and you <hi>hear</hi>) the <hi>Obſequies</hi> now <hi>celebrated</hi> may be, unto <hi>ſome ſoules</hi> among us, <hi>life</hi> from the <hi>dead. Said I not unto thee</hi>
                        <note n="r" place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 11.40.</note> 
                        <hi>that thou ſhouldest</hi> ſee <hi>the glory of God, if thou wouldeſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve? Sure I am, as <hi>ſeeing</hi> is<note n="ſ" place="margin">44.21.6. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2.</note> the preſent, the<note n="t" place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 7.17.12.46. <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.15. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.13, 20.</note> future, the<note n="u" place="margin">3.2. 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2 9. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1.</note> eternal, <hi>recompence</hi> of <hi>believing;</hi> ſo <hi>believing</hi> is<note n="x" place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov:</hi> 1 23. <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſa:</hi> 55.3.</note> the <hi>reward</hi> of <hi>hearing.</hi>
                        <note n="y" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2.</note> By <hi>hearing</hi> cometh <hi>Faith:</hi> And (take this for the main, the chief, and the laſt, <hi>Conſolation</hi> in my <hi>Text</hi>) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever this <hi>grace</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> cometh, there it <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh.</hi> This was the <hi>victorie</hi> which <hi>overcame</hi> this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs trials,</hi> even, his <hi>Faith,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:95939:35"/>
                     <head>By faith <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AND By faith we find<note n="z" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Act.</hi> 16.34.</note> a <hi>joy</hi> in <hi>believing:</hi> that therefore (in this <hi>Bethanie</hi>) in this <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>mourning,</hi> Our <hi>mourning</hi> may be <hi>turned</hi> into <hi>ioy,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> vouchſafe unto us an <hi>effectual,</hi> a <hi>practical,</hi> a <hi>ſanctified, remembrance</hi> of theſe five <hi>Conſiderations.</hi> 1. The like <hi>Duties</hi> which <hi>Abraham</hi> was to <hi>perform,</hi> we are, 2. If we would <hi>perform</hi> them <hi>aright,</hi> we muſt <hi>follow</hi> His <hi>example.</hi> 3. We may <hi>follow</hi> his <hi>example,</hi> if, as He did, we can <hi>believe:</hi> 4. To <hi>obtain</hi> alike <hi>precious faith</hi> with Him, we have <hi>greater Helps</hi> then ever he had. 5. Having <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained</hi> like <hi>precious faith</hi> with him; as he did, ſo we may, of this <hi>divine grace</hi> make <hi>heavenly</hi> Uſes.</p>
                     <p>Firſt I appeal unto that <hi>pride of life</hi> which <hi>ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth</hi> our <hi>costly garments</hi> ſo full of <hi>levitie,</hi> our <hi>buildings</hi> ſo full of <hi>ostentation,</hi> our <hi>tables</hi> ſo full of <hi>exceſs,</hi> and our <hi>purſes</hi> ſo emptie of <hi>coin:</hi> I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal unto that <hi>libertie</hi> (which no man <hi>giveth,</hi> but every of us <hi>taketh</hi>) to do what is <hi>good</hi> in our <hi>own eyes;</hi> that we have the like <hi>prosperitie</hi> to <hi>ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi> with, as had this <hi>Patriarch:</hi> Neither is our <hi>adverſitie</hi> much <hi>un-like,</hi> or <hi>behind,</hi> his: witneſs the <hi>dead body</hi> of this <hi>Iſaac</hi> whom we are now <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up.</hi> Beſide, I have told you at large, that our <hi>frail life</hi> is a <hi>continual warfare:</hi> We are (ye know) <hi>oppoſed</hi> by a <hi>world</hi> of <hi>Wickedneſs.</hi> Through the <hi>lusts</hi> that are within us, the <hi>whole world</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:95939:36"/> cometh a <hi>ſnare</hi> unto our <hi>fleſh,</hi> Our <hi>fleſh</hi> warreth againſt our <hi>ſoul,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Gods Spirit.</hi> Add to theſe the <hi>malice,</hi> the <hi>devices,</hi> the <hi>powers,</hi> the <hi>un-wearineſs,</hi> of <hi>evil Spirits</hi> innumerable, and inviſible: How to <hi>endure</hi> theſe <hi>temptations,</hi> how to <hi>fulfil</hi> thoſe <hi>Duties,</hi> which ſo much <hi>reſemble</hi> the <hi>trials,</hi> the <hi>Duties,</hi> of <hi>Abraham;</hi> it is high time that we <hi>learn,</hi> &amp; <hi>learn</hi> from <hi>Abraham.</hi> For</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Return unto <hi>Gen. XXII.</hi> when his <hi>Iſaac</hi> is <hi>demanded,</hi> how doth the <hi>good old Father</hi> demean himſelf? Doth he <hi>counterfeit</hi> a <hi>ſlumber?</hi> Doth he pretend that, if called he was, he knew it not; that if to his name he <hi>(a)</hi> anſwered, he only <hi>spake in his ſleep?</hi> Doth he impute the <hi>Dream</hi> of his <hi>head</hi> unto ſome <hi>melancholy blood</hi> depreſſing his <hi>heart?</hi> Doth he <hi>construe</hi> that <hi>viſion</hi> of the <hi>night</hi> to be either ſome <hi>flaſhie imagination,</hi> or elſe one of <hi>Satans deluſions?</hi> Noe. The <hi>voice</hi> was <hi>Jehovahs</hi> voice, and (for the <hi>voice</hi> of <hi>Jehovah</hi>) he owneth it: <hi>Subterfuges</hi> he ſeeketh none; <hi>Stagger</hi> he doth not; His God would have no <hi>pleaſure</hi> in him, ſhould he <hi>draw back;</hi> He remembreth <hi>Lots</hi> wife. Hoping to bow the <hi>Lords will</hi> (as an <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbeliever</hi> wreſteth the <hi>Scriptures</hi>) unto his <hi>own bent, Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> conſulted the <hi>Lord</hi> a <hi>third</hi> and <hi>fourth</hi> time, but in <hi>Gods firſt revelation</hi> this <hi>Holy Father</hi> acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſceth: as chearfully <hi>staying himſelf</hi> upon the <hi>Lord</hi> while his <hi>Son</hi> is now <hi>demanded,</hi> as upon the <hi>Lord</hi> he then <hi>Stayed himſelf,</hi> when the ſame <hi>Son</hi> was firſt <hi>promiſed.</hi> Did he <hi>conſult fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood;</hi>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:95939:36"/> unſeen to others, he could let fall half a word which would ſoon make <hi>Servants interpoſe, Sarah contradict</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſlipp <hi>aſide;</hi> but to <hi>prevaricate</hi> he <hi>abhorreth,</hi> as he <hi>abhorreth hypocriſie,</hi> Such is the <hi>ſinceritie</hi> of his <hi>Obedience,</hi> that, until the <hi>hour</hi> of <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> none are of his <hi>counſel;</hi> Such his <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> that at the <hi>hour</hi> of <hi>Sacrifice</hi> (if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Joſephus</hi>) he <hi>perſwadeth</hi> even <hi>Iſaac</hi> himſelf to be of his <hi>confederacie:</hi> He was <hi>armed</hi> againſt every <hi>temptation</hi> with <hi>ſelf denial,</hi> againſt every <hi>exigencie</hi> with <hi>wiſdom,</hi> and againſt every <hi>natural inclination</hi> with <hi>grace;</hi> Without any <hi>reluctancie, repineing,</hi> or <hi>remiſneſs,</hi> he <hi>(c)</hi> ariſeth, and <hi>ariſeth early;</hi> Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of <hi>Servants</hi> he hath, yet <hi>(c)</hi> waiteth not for the <hi>attendance</hi> of any; but doth probably with <hi>his</hi> own <hi>hands</hi> get the <hi>fire</hi> and the <hi>Knife</hi> in a <hi>readineſs;</hi> neither <hi>diſdaineth</hi> he <hi>(c)</hi> to <hi>Saddle</hi> the <hi>aſſe,</hi> yea or to be <hi>(c)</hi> his own <hi>wood cleaver.</hi> Had this <hi>Knife,</hi> this <hi>fire,</hi> this <hi>Wood,</hi> bin provided for ſome <hi>ſolemn Festival;</hi> Were his <hi>Heir</hi> now newly <hi>anointed</hi> with <hi>oyl,</hi> and anon, like<note n="†" place="margin">
                           <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.9. <hi>John</hi> 12.15.</note> 
                        <hi>after-Princes,</hi> to ride that <hi>Sadled aſſe</hi> in <hi>State;</hi> Were he him-ſelf now to ſett a <hi>crown</hi> of <hi>pure gold</hi> upon his <hi>Iſaac's</hi> head, and (that done) to <hi>espouſe</hi> unto <hi>this Son</hi> ſome <hi>Atoſſa,</hi> ſome Quen of <hi>Shebah,</hi> yea or <hi>Rebekah</hi> her ſelf; what could he have done more? nay<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.67.</note> he had not done ſo much: This <hi>pat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tern</hi> may every one of us take out, this <hi>example</hi> may we <hi>imitate.</hi> With <hi>humilitie, ſelf denial,</hi> and <hi>ſubmiſſion;</hi> with <hi>patience, preudnce</hi> and <hi>stedfastneſs</hi> with a <hi>preparedneſs, readineſs,</hi> and <hi>chearfulneſs</hi> of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:95939:37"/> 
                        <hi>mind</hi> may we <hi>offer up</hi> our <hi>Iſaacs,</hi> if, with <hi>Abraham,</hi> we <hi>Sacrifice</hi> them unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice</hi> them unto the <hi>Lord</hi> both in <hi>Faith</hi> and by <hi>Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 <hi>Take heed therefore,</hi> brethren, <hi>leſt there be</hi> in any of you<note n="†" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                        <hi>an</hi> evil heart <hi>of</hi> unbelief <hi>in</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting <hi>from the living God:</hi> For 1. although when we ſhould <hi>offer up</hi> our <hi>Iſaacs</hi> by <hi>Faith,</hi> we have a God to <hi>draw neer</hi> unto, although this <hi>God</hi> be a <hi>living God;</hi> yet <hi>mans heart</hi> naturally <hi>revolteth</hi> from this <hi>living</hi> God: and is therefore a <hi>heart</hi>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro:</hi> 10.20.</note> 
                        <hi>little worth,</hi> an<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5.</note> 
                        <hi>evil heart,</hi> a heart<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Jerem.</hi> 17.9.</note> 
                        <hi>desperately wicked.</hi> 2. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> is an <hi>idleneſs</hi> of <hi>mind</hi> as <hi>neglected,</hi> as <hi>hereditarie;</hi> a <hi>lethargie</hi> contracted<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.5.</note> from our <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb,</hi> a<note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut</hi> 32.20. <hi>Eſa:</hi> 48.8. <hi>Pro:</hi> 22.15.</note> 
                        <hi>frowardneſs</hi> which our <hi>Nurſes</hi> che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in our <hi>childhood,</hi> a <hi>Defect</hi> which in our <hi>minoritie</hi> few <hi>tutors</hi> eye, an <hi>evil</hi> which in our <hi>full age</hi> no <hi>magistrates</hi> puniſh; a <hi>guilt,</hi> an <hi>overſight,</hi> a<note n="f" place="margin">
                           <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.6. <hi>John</hi> 12.35.</note> 
                        <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> which man<note n="g" place="margin">1.5.3.19, 20. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
                        <hi>loveth!</hi> Of <hi>wordly wants,</hi> we are (all of us) very <hi>ſenſible;</hi> but of a <hi>want</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> few (very few) complain: and yet (<hi>mercy, mercy, O</hi> our <hi>God!</hi>)</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Except ye</hi> believe<note n="h" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſa.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.9. <hi>James</hi> 1.8.</note> 
                        <hi>ſurely ye ſhall not be</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. For 2. although the <hi>wages</hi> of every <hi>ſin</hi> is <hi>death, whatſoever</hi> is not of <hi>Faith,</hi> is <hi>Sin.</hi> 3. If God be <hi>against us,</hi> who can be <hi>for us?</hi> but ſo long as <hi>unbelief</hi> hardneth our heart <hi>against God, God</hi> is <hi>againſt us.</hi> 4. Upon him that <hi>believeth not</hi> the <hi>wrath</hi> of <hi>God abideth,</hi> &amp; (ſhould he <hi>cast upon us</hi> the <hi>fierceneſſe</hi> of his <hi>wrath</hi>) who can ſtand before <hi>everlasting burnings?</hi> 5. For that <hi>wretch</hi> who <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth</hi>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:95939:37"/> ſo <hi>bleſſed</hi> a <hi>Creatour,</hi> for that <hi>ſervant</hi> who <hi>controlleth</hi> ſo <hi>wiſe</hi> a <hi>Lord,</hi> for that <hi>Subject</hi> who <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh</hi> ſo <hi>gracious</hi> a <hi>Soveraign,</hi> for that <hi>perſon</hi> who <hi>believeth not</hi> a <hi>God</hi> ſo infinitely <hi>true</hi> &amp;c. No <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> is <hi>hell</hi> enough, no <hi>Hell</hi> hath <hi>torments</hi> enough, no <hi>torments</hi> are too <hi>durable,</hi> too <hi>everlasting,</hi> too <hi>eternal.</hi> Wherefore 6. We muſt even with <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>trembling</hi> workout our <hi>Salvation,</hi> but (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Faith</hi> no <hi>Salvation</hi> is <hi>hoped</hi> for) by <hi>Faith</hi> ye are <hi>ſaved.</hi> 7. Whereas to <hi>glorifie</hi> Him <hi>of</hi> whom, <hi>by</hi> whom, and <hi>for</hi> whom, are <hi>all things,</hi> is the <hi>whole Duty</hi> of <hi>man;</hi> without <hi>Faith</hi> there is no <hi>right understanding</hi> of this <hi>Duty.</hi> So that 8. Whereas<note n="†" place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.34, 36. <hi>Matt:</hi> 24.42, 44 25.13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.3.</note> 
                        <hi>peculiar</hi> unto every <hi>hour</hi> of our <hi>lives,</hi> is the <hi>Duty</hi> of that <hi>hour;</hi> without <hi>Faith</hi> we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not our <hi>Converſation aright,</hi> no not for the <hi>space</hi> of <hi>one moment;</hi> At this inſtant the <hi>truth</hi> now <hi>uttered</hi> profiteth not, if it be not <hi>mixed</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> with <hi>Faith.</hi> Add 9. Whereas it is the <hi>whole happineſs</hi> of <hi>man</hi> to find <hi>favour</hi> in the <hi>ſight</hi> of the <hi>Lord (alwaies</hi> to find <hi>favour</hi> in the <hi>ſight</hi> of the <hi>Lord;) without Faith</hi> it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> to <hi>pleaſe God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Laſtly, <hi>Let the</hi> dead <hi>bury their</hi> dead. No marveil if <hi>without Faith</hi> no <hi>favour</hi> is <hi>obtained</hi> from the <hi>Lord;</hi> ſince without <hi>Faith</hi> we <hi>ſeek</hi> not, nay we <hi>deſire</hi> not, to <hi>pleaſe Him,</hi> if<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> 10.4.14.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3 11.</note> 
                        <hi>pleaſe</hi> him we could. Alas, there is in us (I <hi>tremble</hi> to <hi>ſpeak</hi> it) there is in us an<note n="b" place="margin">8.7.5.10. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.21.</note> 
                        <hi>enmitie</hi> againſt the <hi>great</hi> and <hi>terrible</hi> God! The <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> of every <hi>unbeliever</hi> is<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 51.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
                        <hi>defiled;</hi> his heart is (like himſelf)
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:95939:38"/> 
                        <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>abominable.</hi> How can it be otherwiſe, ſeeing he is<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Jude.</hi> 11.</note> 
                        <hi>twice dead; dead</hi> in <hi>ſin; dead</hi> in <hi>guilt?</hi> Alive unto <hi>ſin,</hi> he is, but <hi>dead</hi> unto <hi>righteouſneſs!</hi> All his works are<note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1.9 14.</note> 
                        <hi>dead works;</hi> therefore <hi>dead works,</hi> becauſe he himſelf continueth<note n="f" place="margin">
                           <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.16.</note> unto every good work <hi>reprobate.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For as in Heaven <hi>unbelief</hi> did put <hi>Lucifer</hi> quite out of the <hi>right uſe</hi> of his <hi>knowledge, love, joy,</hi> &amp;c. then when (unto himſelf and his <hi>combining an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>) he<note n="g" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſa.</hi> 14.14.</note> ſaid <hi>I will be</hi> like <hi>unto the</hi> moſt High: and as in Paradiſe <hi>unbelief</hi> did put <hi>Adam</hi> quite beſide the <hi>right uſe</hi> of his<note n="h" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hebr</hi> 5.14. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.3. <hi>Deut:</hi> 28.28.</note> 
                        <hi>ſenſes,</hi> &amp;c. Then when he alſo<note n="i" place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen</hi> 3.5.</note> ſaid unto himſelf <hi>I will be</hi> as God: So unto the Worlds end the <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>madneſs</hi> of <hi>unbelief</hi> doth and will<note n="k" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>John</hi> 3 6. <hi>Gal:</hi> 5.17.</note> 
                        <hi>distract</hi> every <hi>unbeliever</hi> (ſo <hi>long</hi> and ſo <hi>farr</hi> as he <hi>abideth</hi> in <hi>unbelief</hi>) from the <hi>right</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> uſe both of his <hi>Soul</hi> and of his <hi>body:</hi> Without <hi>Faith</hi> man is unto things <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly,</hi> juſt as a mad man is unto things <hi>earthly</hi> and <hi>ſenſual: raſh, fearleſs, fool hardie.</hi> He ſaith as well in his <hi>actions</hi> as in his heart<note n="l" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14 1.</note> There is no God, for he doth not<note n="m" place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.21.</note> what <hi>God pleaſeth,</hi> but what he<note n="n" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 1.</note> 
                        <hi>lusteth:</hi> He ſaith of God<note n="o" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21.</note> that he is ſuch a one as himſelf, one that regardeth<note n="p" place="margin">73.11.94.7, 8.</note> not <hi>iniquitie,</hi> one that doth<note n="q" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſa.</hi> 41.23.</note> neither <hi>good</hi> (to <hi>reward</hi>); nor <hi>evil</hi> (to <hi>avenge:</hi>) He will be<note n="r" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.3.</note> his <hi>own chuſer,</hi> and conſequently)<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.7.8, 9.</note> his <hi>own God:</hi> Saith he<note n="t" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro</hi> 30.9. <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
                        <hi>who is the</hi> Lord <hi>that I ſhould</hi> obey <hi>him and</hi> deliver <hi>up mine</hi> Iſaac? If I cannot <hi>draw neer</hi> unto God, unleſs I <hi>offer up</hi> my ſon, that I may not <hi>part with</hi> my Son, I will <hi>depart from</hi> my God.</p>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:95939:38"/>
                     <p>Sirs, to give ſight to this <hi>blind</hi> man by expelling this <hi>darkneſs</hi> from his <hi>unbelieving boſom;</hi> to force him to <hi>ſtand in awe,</hi> by tying him up from any more <hi>hardning</hi> his <hi>heart;</hi> to<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.29. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. <hi>Epheſ:</hi> 1.19.</note> 
                        <hi>over-rule</hi> ſo<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 2.14.3 18, 19.</note> 
                        <hi>foo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and ſo<note n="a" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.3, 18. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 8.6.17.9. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Act.</hi> 19 36.</note> 
                        <hi>raſh</hi> an<note n="b" place="margin">
                           <hi>Job.</hi> 9.4. <hi>Prov:</hi> 8.36.</note> 
                        <hi>enemie</hi> of<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1.</note> 
                        <hi>God;</hi> to<note n="d" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5.</note> 
                        <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm</hi> him of thoſe<note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4.14. <hi>John</hi> 5.44. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21, 24, 26.28. 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.8.</note> 
                        <hi>fiery darts</hi> wherewith he<note n="f" place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov:</hi> 12.26. <hi>and</hi> 13.15. <hi>Eccle.</hi> 9.18. <hi>Phil:</hi> 3.18, 19.</note> 
                        <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheiveth</hi>
                        <note n="g" place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov:</hi> 13.5. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 7.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Jude</hi> 15.</note> 
                        <hi>himſelf</hi> and<note n="h" place="margin">
                           <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.6, 12. <hi>John</hi> 15.19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. and 15.33. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.13. 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 4.4. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſhu:</hi> 22.20.</note> 
                        <hi>others;</hi> to<note n="i" place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. from <hi>v.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>6. unto <hi>v.</hi> 34. <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.21. with 8.15. and 9.35. and 11.9. and 14.17, 18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 2 30. and 29.4. <hi>Joſhu.</hi> 11.30. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.25, 30. 1 <hi>King</hi> 12.15. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 25.16. <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.15. <hi>John</hi> 8.47. and 12.40.</note> 
                        <hi>convince</hi> him that there is<note n="k" place="margin">2 <hi>Chron</hi> 25.18, 19. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>7.4. and 36.8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.31. <hi>Act.</hi> 9 5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.21.</note> no <hi>fighting</hi> againſt the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>hoſts;</hi> to<note n="l" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 13.9. <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>a.</hi> 1.16, 17, 18.</note> 
                        <hi>reduce</hi> him unto a<note n="m" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſa</hi> 2.11. <hi>Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>em.</hi> 8 6. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74, 79.</note> 
                        <hi>right uſe</hi> of<note n="n" place="margin">
                           <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.24. <hi>Pſal</hi> 50.23.</note> his <hi>Senſes</hi> and of<note n="o" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.7, 8, 9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20.</note> 
                        <hi>Himſelf;</hi> to<note n="p" place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 1 23. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 13 27. <hi>John</hi> 8.43, 47.</note> 
                        <hi>perſwade</hi> him to<note n="q" place="margin">
                           <hi>James</hi> 4.7, 8.</note> 
                        <hi>Submit</hi>
                        <note n="r" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.28. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.2.</note> 
                        <hi>draw near</hi> and<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19, 20.</note> 
                        <hi>reconcile</hi> his<note n="t" place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9.</note> 
                        <hi>heart</hi> unto his<note n="u" place="margin">
                           <hi>Jerem.</hi> 10.7.</note> 
                        <hi>God:</hi> to<note n="x" place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.21. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.40. and 29.19, 20. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.24. and 63.4. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.29.</note> 
                        <hi>winn</hi> him to<note n="y" place="margin">
                           <hi>Mark</hi> 10.30.31.</note> not <hi>with-hold</hi> but to<note n="z" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
                        <hi>offer up</hi>
                        <note n="†" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11.</note> unto the <hi>Lord</hi> his<note n="*" place="margin">116.13, 16.</note> 
                        <hi>Iſaac</hi>
                        <note n="a" place="margin">110.3.</note> 
                        <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly</hi>
                        <note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.10. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.17.</note> 
                        <hi>chearfully</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.28.</note> 
                        <hi>acceptably:</hi> to<note n="d" place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal</hi> 51.10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.4. with 30.6.</note> 
                        <hi>work</hi> ſo<note n="e" place="margin">
                           <hi>Jerem.</hi> 30.21.</note> 
                        <hi>great,</hi> ſo<note n="f" place="margin">
                           <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13.</note> 
                        <hi>heavenly</hi> a <hi>change</hi> of <hi>mind</hi> as this, <hi>One thing</hi> is<note n="g" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17, 18.</note> 
                        <hi>neceſſary; viz</hi> the<note n="h" place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.42. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1.</note> 
                        <hi>Faith</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> elect. For as<note n="i" place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16, 17, 18, 20, 21. and 11.7, 22.</note> 
                        <hi>reprobation</hi> pre-ſuppoſeth an<note n="k" place="margin">11.5, 6, 28.</note> 
                        <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection,</hi> and as<note n="l" place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1.</note> 
                        <hi>truth</hi> precedeth <hi>errour,</hi> ſo (if rightly conſidered) there was a<note n="m" place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Jude</hi> 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28.</note> 
                        <hi>belief</hi> before there was<note n="n" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10.11.</note> 
                        <hi>unbelief:</hi> Wherefore <hi>prove</hi> your <hi>own ſelves</hi>
                        <note n="o" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5.</note> 
                        <hi>examine</hi> your ſelves whether ye be in the <hi>Faith,</hi> or whether ye be<note n="p" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
                        <hi>concerning</hi> the <hi>Faith</hi> reprobates. Know</p>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10. and 4.6. <hi>Act.</hi> 13.38.</note>
                     <p n="4">
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:95939:39"/>4. Or ever he <hi>ordained</hi> any <hi>worlds,</hi> the <hi>one,</hi> the <hi>true,</hi> the <hi>good,</hi> JEHOVAH, (ſeeing he <hi>inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi> both <hi>etrnitie</hi> and <hi>immenſitie!</hi>) was the ſame <hi>divine exiſtence, ſelf-exiſtence, ſelf-ſubſisting ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stence,</hi> that now is. He could before all <hi>predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> as well as now ſay I AM: I (ever<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Num.</hi> 23.9.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone) am <hi>peace;</hi> I (a <hi>Father</hi> ever begetting, a <hi>Son</hi> ever begotten, a <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> ever proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) am (not <hi>confuſion</hi> but) <hi>Order:</hi> I am <hi>life, light, puritie, holineſs</hi> &amp;c. 2 As he could ever ſay I AM, he could alſo ever ſay I AM WHAT I AM; when <hi>Pilate</hi> would not <hi>alter</hi> his <hi>writing,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>WHAT</hi> I have <hi>written,</hi> I have <hi>written;</hi> So (before all Worlds) could <hi>God</hi> ſay <hi>I am,</hi> and am <hi>well pleaſed</hi> in <hi>What</hi> I <hi>am:</hi> As I <hi>do not,</hi> ſo I <hi>would not,</hi> ceaſe to be <hi>life, light, puritie, holineſs</hi> &amp;c. 3 End-leſs is that <hi>delight</hi> which I take in what by <hi>nature</hi> I ever <hi>was,</hi> ever <hi>ſhall he,</hi> and now <hi>am.</hi> My <hi>bleſſedneſs,</hi> my <hi>glory,</hi> my <hi>rejoycing</hi> is neither <hi>of,</hi> nor <hi>from,</hi> others, but <hi>from</hi> and <hi>in</hi> My ſelf; I am <hi>full</hi> and <hi>abound:</hi> No <hi>fleſh,</hi> no <hi>Saints,</hi> no <hi>Worlds</hi> do I need, for I, the <hi>three</hi> divine <hi>perſons,</hi> am unto <hi>Our ſelf</hi> a THE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ATRE. So that 4 It is in <hi>mine election</hi> whether I will, or will not, <hi>determine</hi> to be a <hi>Creatour;</hi> if
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:95939:39"/> to be a <hi>Creatour</hi> I do <hi>determine, Good</hi> I <hi>am,</hi> and all <hi>my works</hi> ſhall <hi>cal</hi> me <hi>good. Good</hi> I <hi>do,</hi> and <hi>good</hi> I <hi>will do</hi> unto all ſuch as <hi>abide</hi> in <hi>my goodneſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 He <hi>spake,</hi> It <hi>was:</hi> Brethren, (well may we <hi>beleeve</hi> in God!) <hi>Jehovah,</hi> to <hi>confirm</hi> his <hi>promiſe</hi> to this <hi>Patriarch</hi> by an <hi>oath,</hi> becauſe he could <hi>ſwear</hi> by <hi>no greater, ſware</hi> by <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:</hi> So to <hi>create</hi> a <hi>world of bleſſings,</hi> becauſe a <hi>better pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern</hi> he could not <hi>take,</hi> he <hi>took</hi> a <hi>pattern</hi> from Himſelf: God is <hi>one,</hi> ſuch is the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe: God</hi> is <hi>perfect, immenſe, eternall;</hi> The <hi>World</hi> is <hi>round, wide, laſting.</hi> In <hi>God</hi> is <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>order.</hi> From the <hi>leaſt atom</hi> to the <hi>higheſt Angel</hi> is found <hi>order</hi> and <hi>harmonie.</hi> God <hi>ſelf ſubſisteth;</hi> even in <hi>ſenſeleſs elements</hi> is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted</hi> a <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>ſelfe preſervation: God</hi> is <hi>bleſſed,</hi> In <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature</hi> having <hi>life</hi> is <hi>imprinted</hi> a <hi>desire</hi> not only of <hi>being,</hi> but of <hi>wel-being</hi> God <hi>changeth not;</hi> The <hi>wel-being</hi> of all his <hi>works</hi> is <hi>placed</hi> in a <hi>not changing</hi> that <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>nature</hi> whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they were <hi>ordained.</hi> Which <hi>law</hi> giveth unto <hi>every fleſh</hi> its <hi>own ſeede:</hi> unto <hi>every ſeede</hi> its <hi>own body;</hi> unto <hi>every body,</hi> its <hi>own Soul;</hi> unto <hi>every Soul</hi> its <hi>own felicitie.</hi> God is a <hi>free a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent;</hi> As <hi>ſenſible creatures</hi> have a <hi>free choice</hi> to <hi>like,</hi> or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,</hi> what unto their <hi>ſenſes</hi> ſeemeth <hi>pleaſing,</hi> or <hi>displeaſing:</hi> ſo <hi>reaſonable creatures</hi> ſhould alſo have a <hi>free will</hi> to <hi>chuſe,</hi> or <hi>refuſe</hi> whatſoever to their <hi>beſt underſtanding</hi> ſeemeth <hi>truly good,</hi> or <hi>truly evill.</hi> In <hi>attracting ſustenance,</hi> or in <hi>propagating</hi> their <hi>kind,</hi> to confine <hi>brutes</hi> to be as <hi>inſenſible</hi> as <hi>trees</hi> are, or <hi>men</hi> to be as <hi>irrationall</hi> as <hi>brutes</hi> are, were to <hi>reject</hi> the <hi>wiſdom</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Even ſo to limit <hi>man</hi> to be <hi>ſenſuall,</hi> but not <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous;</hi> to be <hi>vertuous</hi> but not <hi>holy;</hi> to <hi>mind</hi> things <hi>Earthly,</hi> but not <hi>things Heavenly;</hi> to <hi>ſtay himſelfe</hi> upon the <hi>creature,</hi> but not upon the <hi>Creatour;</hi> to <hi>love</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> but not the <hi>Lord God;</hi> were to <hi>require</hi> him to be, <hi>concerning</hi> the <hi>faith</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> elect, <hi>reprobate.</hi> For the <hi>Law</hi> whereunto <hi>God</hi> elected <hi>men</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>
                        <pb n="72" facs="tcp:95939:40"/> was, He that <hi>lifteth</hi> up his <hi>Soul</hi> is not <hi>upright:</hi> (and if not <hi>upright,</hi> a <hi>loſt Angel,</hi> a <hi>dead man:</hi>) but the <hi>juſt</hi> ſhall <hi>live</hi> by <hi>faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. To you who <hi>bewail</hi> your <hi>unbelief</hi> I ſpeak it. Until God <hi>appeared</hi> unto him in <hi>Meſopotamia, Abraham</hi> (that <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of the <hi>faithful!</hi>) never had thoſe <hi>prepared helps,</hi> thoſe <hi>effective meanes,</hi> of <hi>obtaining</hi> this <hi>precious grace,</hi> this <hi>faith</hi> of Gods <hi>elect,</hi> which the <hi>verieſt reprobate</hi> of you all <hi>at this time</hi> poſſeſſeth. He was <hi>bred up</hi> among <hi>aliens</hi> and <hi>strangers</hi> to <hi>grace,</hi> The <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> covereth our <hi>Iſland</hi> as the <hi>waters</hi> cover the <hi>Sea:</hi> He was, ye were not, the <hi>unclean Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of <hi>unbeleeving Parents;</hi> He <hi>could not</hi> ſay <hi>Thou</hi> haſt <hi>looſed</hi> my <hi>bands,</hi> for <hi>I am</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> of thy <hi>hand-maid;</hi> but <hi>Ye</hi> were by <hi>praier</hi> and by <hi>baptiſme</hi> conſecrated to <hi>your God</hi> in your <hi>infancie;</hi> and were <hi>from</hi> your <hi>infancie</hi> nurtured up in <hi>good knowledge.</hi> 2. He was (like S. <hi>Paul</hi>) in <hi>journeyings often;</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding <hi>citie</hi> he had <hi>none;</hi> but was ever <hi>unſetled:</hi> As for you, ye in <hi>ſure dwellings,</hi> and in <hi>quiet reſting places</hi> have <hi>retired<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>leiſure</hi> to <hi>devote</hi> your ſelves to <hi>praier, meditation</hi> &amp;c. 3. <hi>Eight</hi> or <hi>nine</hi> times did <hi>Jehovah</hi> converſe with <hi>Him,</hi> with you he <hi>converſeth</hi> eightie <hi>times</hi> nine <hi>times. Twice</hi> or <hi>thrice</hi> was the <hi>Gospel</hi> preached unto Him (and that too) very <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> To you it <hi>ſhineth</hi> as <hi>clearely,</hi> and, in a <hi>ſort,</hi> as <hi>frequently,</hi> as <hi>day-light.</hi> What a <hi>ſmall pittance</hi> of <hi>ſaving knowledge</hi> could he <hi>glean</hi> from the <hi>traditions</hi> of his <hi>fore-fathers</hi> in <hi>compariſon</hi> of what may be <hi>learned</hi> by you; <hi>by you</hi> who may all <hi>know</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> from the <hi>least</hi> to the <hi>greatest, by you</hi> who are in Gods <hi>Scriptures</hi> all <hi>taught</hi> of <hi>God?</hi> 4. <hi>Christ</hi> is the <hi>viſion,</hi> the <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage,</hi> of the <hi>father</hi> of <hi>mercies;</hi> the <hi>Gospel</hi> is the <hi>image,</hi> the <hi>face,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> Of this <hi>Gospel,</hi> of this <hi>face</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> more is <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested</hi> unto you, then ever was <hi>revealed</hi> unto <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. As <hi>zeal</hi> without <hi>knowledge</hi> is the <hi>mother</hi> of <hi>perſecution,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:95939:40"/> idolatrie, ſuperstition, enthuſiaſm, ſchiſm, hereſie, ſedition, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,</hi> &amp;c. So <hi>knowledge</hi> without <hi>zeal</hi> begetteth <hi>atheiſm, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneſs, hypocricie, pride.</hi> &amp;c. But that which maketh <hi>mans knowledge</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to be <hi>mans ſalvation,</hi> is the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>faith ſanctifying</hi> unto him <hi>what he knoweth</hi> For. 1. <hi>By faith</hi> we <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand</hi>—one <hi>office</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> is to <hi>enlighten</hi> the <hi>understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> 2. <hi>By faith</hi> Moſes <hi>refuſed, chuſing rather</hi> — viz As <hi>faith diſcerneth</hi> what is <hi>good</hi> ſo <hi>faith embraceth,</hi> what <hi>good</hi> it <hi>diſcerneth.</hi> 3. A third <hi>effect</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> is to <hi>purifie</hi> the <hi>heart.</hi> 4. <hi>By faith</hi> they <hi>ſubdued</hi> and <hi>obtained</hi>—When faith hath ſo <hi>instructed</hi> the <hi>heart,</hi> that it no longer <hi>beleeveth</hi> a <hi>lie;</hi> and hath ſo <hi>corrected</hi> the <hi>mind,</hi> that it <hi>holdeth</hi> not the <hi>truth</hi> in <hi>unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs;</hi> When a <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>truth,</hi> of the <hi>whole truth,</hi> (yea and of <hi>nothing</hi> but the <hi>truth</hi>) freeth the <hi>head</hi> from <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour;</hi> and when a <hi>love</hi> of that <hi>truth</hi> freeth the <hi>heart</hi> from <hi>diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience;</hi> when we <hi>like</hi> to <hi>retain God</hi> in our <hi>Knowledge;</hi> then do we <hi>apprehend</hi> that for which alſo we are <hi>apprehended</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> When ye <hi>ſeeke</hi> not your <hi>own wills,</hi> but your <hi>Gods will;</hi> when ye with <hi>meekeneſs,</hi> and with <hi>earnestneſs, ſearch,</hi> &amp; <hi>wait,</hi> and <hi>watch,</hi> and <hi>trie,</hi> whether by his <hi>word</hi> of <hi>life</hi> God will <hi>make</hi> your <hi>heart,</hi> as <hi>Abrahams</hi> was, <hi>faithful;</hi> then ye <hi>ſow</hi> to the <hi>spirit;</hi> And as what was <hi>born</hi> of your <hi>fleſh,</hi> was <hi>fleſh;</hi> ſo what is <hi>born</hi> of <hi>Gods spirit,</hi> is <hi>spirit:</hi> For ſuch as <hi>wait</hi> upon <hi>God</hi> in His <hi>waies,</hi> them <hi>God meeteth;</hi> and whom <hi>God meeteth,</hi> in them, by his <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>adoption,</hi> he <hi>formeth</hi> the <hi>quickning ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus. Brethren,</hi> Hereby may ye <hi>know</hi> whether ye have, with <hi>faithful Abraham, believed</hi> unto <hi>righteouſneſs:</hi> If unto <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> ye have <hi>beleeved,</hi> then have ye <hi>paſſed</hi> from the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>unbeliefe</hi> wherein ye were <hi>born,</hi> to the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye were <hi>baptized.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. To whom <hi>God giveth</hi> a <hi>power,</hi> to them he alſo <hi>vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth</hi> a <hi>habit,</hi> of <hi>beleeving:</hi> Having therefore <hi>obtained</hi> like <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:95939:41"/> faith</hi> with <hi>Him,</hi> imitate ye the <hi>Patriarch</hi> in my <hi>Text.</hi> of this <hi>good</hi> and <hi>perfect gift</hi> which <hi>cometh</hi> down <hi>from above</hi> May ye (<hi>ever</hi> make ye) <hi>ſeaſonable,</hi> and <hi>ſanctified,</hi> Uſes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That in you the <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>God</hi> may be <hi>revealed</hi> from <hi>faith</hi> to <hi>faith,</hi> add to your <hi>faith Knowledge.</hi> For this end, let the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> dwell in you <hi>richly,</hi> and in <hi>all wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> There <hi>can not</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> be a <hi>higher object</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> then the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> neither, <hi>can</hi> there be <hi>upon earth</hi> any <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> equal to what we <hi>learn</hi> in <hi>Holy writ.</hi> No <hi>truth</hi> is <hi>worthy</hi> to be <hi>compared</hi> unto <hi>Scripture truths;</hi> neither is any <hi>Scripture-truth</hi> comparable to <hi>Goſpel revelations: Goſpel revelations</hi> are <hi>mysteries,</hi> great <hi>misteries! Misteries</hi> which <hi>immediately concern</hi> a <hi>reconciliation</hi> between <hi>God provoked,</hi> and <hi>man offending!</hi> Lay up therefore in your <hi>heart,</hi> as <hi>Manna</hi> in a <hi>golden pott;</hi> ſtore up in your <hi>memorie,</hi> as <hi>Oracles</hi> in the <hi>Ark</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> the <hi>Goſpel-treaſures</hi> of <hi>ſpiritual truth,</hi> and <hi>wiſdom:</hi> The <hi>best object</hi> of mans <hi>best understanding</hi> is <hi>that truth</hi> which is in <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. That that <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> which is the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may <hi>free</hi> you as well from the <hi>errour</hi> of your <hi>way,</hi> as from <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoughts;</hi> that ye may be <hi>renewed,</hi> as well in <hi>practice,</hi> as in <hi>Knowledge;</hi> that ye may be, as wel <hi>un-corrupted</hi> in your <hi>mind,</hi> as <hi>un-deceived</hi> in your <hi>judgment;</hi> Receive, with <hi>every truth,</hi> a <hi>love</hi> of that <hi>truth;</hi> that a <hi>love</hi> of <hi>every revealed truth</hi> ye may <hi>receive, purifie</hi> ye your <hi>heart</hi> by <hi>faith;</hi> that <hi>by faith</hi> ye may <hi>purifie</hi> your <hi>heart,</hi> ſeeing there is no <hi>example, threat, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> or <hi>rhetorick,</hi> like unto <hi>Scripture examples, threats, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>rhetorick,</hi> Let <hi>theſe,</hi> let <hi>all theſe,</hi> have a <hi>due force</hi> and a <hi>full power</hi> over your <hi>ſincerest affections:</hi> ſo <hi>conſult</hi> Holy <hi>writ</hi> as who are therein <hi>conſulting</hi> even <hi>God Himſelf;</hi> So <hi>obey</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Writ,</hi> as the <hi>Word</hi> of a <hi>God,</hi> as the <hi>word</hi> of a <hi>God</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>to you;</hi> as the <hi>voice</hi> of the <hi>gracious Jehovah</hi> ſo <hi>ſpeaking</hi>
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:95939:41"/> with you, as he ſome times <hi>spake</hi> with his <hi>friend Abraham,</hi> even <hi>face</hi> to <hi>face:</hi> Oh <hi>Sirs,</hi> as the <hi>beſt object</hi> of your <hi>best un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding,</hi> ſo the moſt <hi>delightful object</hi> of your <hi>pureſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> is the <hi>good nature</hi> of <hi>Emannuel, Jehovah, Jeſus.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Whereas, from <hi>Abrahams ſelf denials,</hi> I <hi>preſſed a ſelf-deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> upon all ſuch <hi>masters, parents,</hi> concerned <hi>officers,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates</hi> as <hi>may,</hi> and <hi>ſhould</hi> befriend <hi>Souls</hi> under their <hi>tuition;</hi> (Old things are <hi>paſſed away:</hi>) I now <hi>urge</hi> the <hi>example,</hi> not of <hi>Abraham repreſenting,</hi> but of the <hi>true father</hi> of <hi>many nations</hi> by <hi>Abraham repreſented:</hi> The <hi>father</hi> of <hi>all men,</hi> when there was <hi>no Arm to help, spared</hi> not his <hi>own Son,</hi> but <hi>delivered</hi> him up <hi>for us all!</hi> And ſhall <hi>worldly favour,</hi> or <hi>neighbourly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> prevent you from <hi>imitating</hi> the <hi>merciful example,</hi> of a <hi>compaſſionate God? If</hi> the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> if the <hi>example</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> findeth <hi>faith</hi> in your <hi>hearts,</hi> O ye <hi>Rulers,</hi> neither let <hi>Souls</hi> ſtupidly <hi>ignorant</hi> eſcape <hi>untaught</hi> and <hi>unchatechiſed;</hi> neither <hi>tollerate</hi> ye thoſe <hi>unlawful meetings</hi> which <hi>wrest</hi> Holy <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> to the <hi>hazard</hi> of <hi>themſelves,</hi> and of this <hi>Kingdom.</hi> 1. (Witneſs our late <hi>civil Warrs,</hi>) As <hi>evil words</hi> corrupt <hi>good manners,</hi> ſo a <hi>little leaven</hi> leaveneth the <hi>whole lump:</hi> A <hi>cancer</hi> in the <hi>mouth</hi> is a <hi>pernicious diſeaſe:</hi> even ſo much that <hi>Christ</hi> hateth that we ſhould <hi>ſuffer</hi> among us the <hi>doctrine</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> or of the <hi>Nicolitans.</hi> 2. When the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>man took</hi> a <hi>farr journey,</hi> he gave <hi>authoritie</hi> to his Servants: If <hi>Law-givers, Lawes,</hi> and <hi>Judges protect</hi> mens <hi>cattle, lands,</hi> and <hi>limbs,</hi> from <hi>violence;</hi> much more let them guard mens <hi>memories, affections, understandings</hi> and <hi>conſciences</hi> from the <hi>ſubtiltie</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of <hi>ſeducers,</hi> and of <hi>Satan.</hi> 3. <hi>Seditious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles rebel</hi> againſt <hi>man, profane atheists rebel</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> but the <hi>Holy conformist rebelleth</hi> againſt <hi>neither;</hi> yea he is therefore <hi>loyal</hi> to his <hi>Soveraign,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>obedient</hi> to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:95939:42"/> his <hi>God.</hi> 4. Is not the <hi>body</hi> more then <hi>raiment?</hi> and is not the <hi>Soul</hi> more then the <hi>Body?</hi> What ſhall his <hi>dread</hi> Majeſties <hi>native</hi> Subjects <hi>give</hi> in <hi>exchange</hi> for their <hi>Souls?</hi> 5. It is the people <hi>laden</hi> with <hi>iniquity</hi> that is the <hi>people</hi> of Gods <hi>wrath,</hi> but a <hi>righteous</hi> people is a <hi>proſperous</hi> people: then ſhall his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Subjects <hi>flouriſh,</hi> when their <hi>Soules proſper.</hi> 6. While upon <hi>Lords daies</hi> and other <hi>daies ſett a part</hi> for <hi>religious aſſemblies</hi> and <hi>duties,</hi> ſome <hi>gadd</hi> about to <hi>change</hi> their <hi>way,</hi> and others <hi>ſit idle</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> God <hi>loſeth</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>full</hi> and <hi>publick congregations, worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances.</hi> During the <hi>tyrannie</hi> of <hi>Oliver</hi> the <hi>Rebel, orthodox Ministers</hi> were <hi>ſequeſtred</hi> from their <hi>parochial congregations,</hi> Under the <hi>Clemencie</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> let not <hi>parochial congregations</hi> be <hi>ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred</hi> from their <hi>orthodox Miniſters.</hi> In ſhort, ſo many as <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiſe</hi> him ſhall be <hi>lightly esteemed,</hi> but ſuch as <hi>honour God,</hi> them <hi>God</hi> will <hi>honour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. Whereas I <hi>convinced</hi> you, that the <hi>burden, ſharpneſs,</hi> &amp; <hi>number,</hi> of our <hi>trials;</hi> are <hi>light afflictions</hi> in <hi>compariſon</hi> of the <hi>temptations</hi> of <hi>Abraham;</hi> behold a <hi>greater</hi> then <hi>Abraham</hi> is here. Conſider Him that endured ſuch <hi>contradiction</hi> of <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> Conſider <hi>Jeſus</hi> by <hi>Iſaac tipified,</hi> and you will <hi>learn</hi> of him to <hi>poſſeſs</hi> your <hi>Souls</hi> in <hi>patience: Faith</hi> inſtructeth us how to <hi>take pleaſure</hi> in <hi>afflictions,</hi> and to <hi>taste</hi> a <hi>joy</hi> even <hi>in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations,</hi> Remove your <hi>eyes</hi> from the <hi>dead body</hi> of our <hi>depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted friend</hi> unto the <hi>body</hi> of <hi>Christ crucified,</hi> you will then, in <hi>lieu</hi> of <hi>mourning</hi> for an <hi>onely Son,</hi> even <hi>aspire</hi> a <hi>fellowſhip</hi> in <hi>Chriſts ſufferings.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. Behold I ſhew you a <hi>mysterie.</hi> The ſame faith which <hi>teacheth</hi> us to <hi>ſeek righteouſneſs</hi> not by <hi>works,</hi> but by <hi>grace;</hi> doth alſo <hi>stirr</hi> us up to <hi>live just</hi> toward our <hi>neighbour,</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and our God. When <hi>by faith</hi> Abraham <hi>offered up his</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac, he <hi>lived just</hi> to his <hi>Son, true</hi> to <hi>himſelf, upright</hi> toward
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:95939:42"/> his <hi>God.</hi> 1. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright</hi> toward <hi>Jehovah,</hi> for <hi>Jehovah</hi> had a <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter right</hi> in <hi>Iſaac,</hi> then the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> ever, either <hi>had,</hi> or could <hi>have<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> 2. <hi>True</hi> to <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> for had he <hi>lifted</hi> up his <hi>Soul,</hi> he had <hi>ceaſed</hi> to be <hi>upright.</hi> 3. <hi>Juſt</hi> to his <hi>Son,</hi> for it was the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> not onely to <hi>live,</hi> but to <hi>die,</hi> unto the <hi>Lord;</hi> Bleſſed is that man which endureth temptation; Would ye <hi>endure</hi> to the end? Would ye have <hi>preſent victorie</hi> over your <hi>preſent conflict? Fight</hi> the <hi>good fight</hi> of <hi>faith:</hi> Who ſo would be <hi>justified,</hi> muſt be <hi>juſtified</hi> not by <hi>works,</hi> but by <hi>faith;</hi> and he that would <hi>order</hi> his <hi>converſation aright,</hi> muſt <hi>uſe</hi> his <hi>knowledge aright;</hi> he muſt make the <hi>best uſe which he can,</hi> not onely of his <hi>reaſon,</hi> but of his <hi>faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. <hi>Faith</hi> fixeth <hi>one eye</hi> upon the <hi>Duty</hi> ſet before us, and the <hi>other eye</hi> upon the <hi>promiſe annexed</hi> to that <hi>Duty; Faith</hi> verily <hi>beleeveth</hi> that there is a <hi>reward</hi> for the <hi>righteous:</hi> In the <hi>mount</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> was <hi>Jehovah</hi> ſeen. By laying that <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> which his <hi>father</hi> could not <hi>lift,</hi> over the <hi>altar</hi> upon the <hi>Wood, Iſaac</hi> his <hi>mouth</hi> was <hi>filled</hi> with <hi>laughter:</hi> 1. He <hi>ſaw</hi> &amp; <hi>heard</hi> an <hi>Angel</hi> ſent from <hi>Heaven</hi> to find <hi>a way</hi> for his <hi>eſcape;</hi> 2. He did not <hi>die,</hi> but <hi>live;</hi> 3. He <hi>lived,</hi> and <hi>lived</hi> a <hi>type,</hi> a <hi>figure,</hi> a <hi>pledge</hi> of <hi>Christs</hi> and in <hi>Christ,</hi> of our <hi>reſurrection</hi> &amp; <hi>Life:</hi> By not <hi>with-holding</hi> his <hi>Son, Abraham</hi> received <hi>praiſe</hi> from his <hi>God,</hi> yea and, with <hi>praiſes, bleſſings; Abraham</hi> ſaw <hi>Christs day</hi> and was <hi>glad:</hi> From the <hi>faith</hi> both of <hi>Abraham</hi> &amp; of <hi>Iſaac Jehovah</hi> Himſelf received <hi>preſent</hi> yea and <hi>in all ages future Glory;</hi> They who <hi>know</hi> His <hi>name</hi> will <hi>trust</hi> in it And yet ſhew I unto you more <hi>excellent things</hi> then <hi>theſe.</hi> For</p>
                     <p n="7">7. The ſame <hi>faith</hi> which <hi>enureth</hi> us to be ever <hi>at once</hi> juſt to our <hi>neighbour,</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and our <hi>God,</hi> worketh upon our <hi>good nature;</hi> it <hi>worketh</hi> in us a diſpoſition to be (like <hi>Christ) harmeleſs</hi> and <hi>blameleſs:</hi> 2. An <hi>emulation</hi> to <hi>put</hi> on the <hi>Lord' Jeſus:</hi> To them that <hi>beleeve</hi> it is <hi>meate</hi> &amp; <hi>drink</hi> to <hi>studie Christ,</hi>
                        <pb n="78" facs="tcp:95939:43"/> to <hi>learn Christ,</hi> and to <hi>live Christ:</hi> yea 3. <hi>Faith heightneth</hi> us to <hi>imitate</hi> (with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>) the <hi>God</hi> and <hi>father</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> it <hi>cheriſheth</hi> in us a <hi>filial delight</hi> of being <hi>followers</hi> of his <hi>Father,</hi> and of our <hi>Father,</hi> as <hi>dear Children: Abba Father,</hi> thou art <hi>long-ſuffering, patient, good, merciful, righteous, liberal, pure, holy, loving</hi> &amp;c. Oh make us, make us (like thy ſelf,) <hi>long-ſuffering.</hi> &amp;c. 4. By <hi>faith</hi> we <hi>rest aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured</hi> that our <hi>fore-runner</hi> hath, in <hi>Heaven, prepared manſions</hi> and <hi>princely Lodgings</hi> for us who believe in Him.</p>
                     <p>To conclude, by <hi>faith</hi> we <hi>reckon</hi> our ſelves therefore <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heires</hi> with <hi>Christ,</hi> becauſe, as he is by <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo <hi>we</hi> are by a <hi>spirit</hi> of <hi>adoption,</hi> priviledged to be the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> all things are <hi>ours,</hi> becauſe we are <hi>Christs,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is <hi>Gods; Gods</hi> in whom <hi>God</hi> is well <hi>pleaſed,</hi> God is the <hi>Lord</hi> not of the <hi>dead,</hi> but of the <hi>living;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Dust</hi> ſhall <hi>give up</hi> her <hi>dead:</hi> True, the <hi>Soul</hi> of our <hi>dear friend</hi> is <hi>ſeparated</hi> from his <hi>body;</hi> nevertheleſs, by <hi>faith</hi> we <hi>eye</hi> our <hi>Mediator</hi> as <hi>bone</hi> of his <hi>bone</hi> and <hi>fleſh</hi> of his <hi>fleſh:</hi> Faith <hi>giveth</hi> us to <hi>understand;</hi> that, ſince <hi>Chriſt</hi> and we are <hi>one body,</hi> together with his <hi>dead body</hi> ſhall our <hi>dead bodies</hi> ariſe; and ſhall therefore ariſe as his <hi>dead body</hi> did <hi>ariſe,</hi> partly becauſe they that are <hi>joyned</hi> unto the <hi>Lord,</hi> are <hi>one spirit;</hi> and partly becauſe (witneſs <hi>Enoch, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> &amp; the <hi>bleſsed Jeſus</hi>) there is one <hi>fleſh</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> another <hi>fleſh</hi> of <hi>beaſts.</hi> The <hi>fleſh</hi> of <hi>beasts,</hi> like their <hi>mortal Soules,</hi> periſheth for ever; The <hi>fleſh</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> the <hi>dead body</hi> of our <hi>dear friend,</hi> like <hi>leafe, Gold,</hi> naturally <hi>aſcendeth</hi> unto the ſame <hi>fingers,</hi> unto the ſame Creatour, who <hi>curiouſly</hi> wrought it upon <hi>earth,</hi> that he might exalt it unto <hi>glory</hi> in <hi>Heaven:</hi> To which <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> he bring us by his <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and by his <hi>Son;</hi> To <hi>whom,</hi> with <hi>Himſelf,</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>all things,</hi> be <hi>dominion</hi> and <hi>ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ever <hi>aſcribed,</hi> Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. <hi>116.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>I beleeved, <hi>therefore</hi> have <hi>I</hi> ſpoken.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:95939:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
